<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Liturgy's vindicated by the dissenters, or, The lawfulness of forms of prayer and liturgies proved from the very texts of Scripture urged against them by John Bunyan and the dissenters / by the author of the Religious conference between a minister and his parishioner about infant baptism.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34970</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14917579</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14917579</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102911</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47748)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102911)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1573:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Liturgy's vindicated by the dissenters, or, The lawfulness of forms of prayer and liturgies proved from the very texts of Scripture urged against them by John Bunyan and the dissenters / by the author of the Religious conference between a minister and his parishioner about infant baptism.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 111 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for C. Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Leslie by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102911:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Liturgy's Vindicated BY THE DISSENTERS: Or, the Lawfulneſs of <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Liturgies;</hi> PROVED From the very Texts of Scripture urged againſt them, by <hi>John Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yan</hi> and the <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Author of the <hi>Religious Conference</hi> between a Miniſter and his Pariſhioner, about <hi>Infant</hi> Baptiſm.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Pet. 3.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In which are ſomethings hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scriptures, to their own Deſtruction.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>C. Brome,</hi> at the Gun, at the Weſt end of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:102911:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102911:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <p>A PREFACE, giving an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Undertaking, and <hi>ſecret Juggle</hi> of <hi>ſome,</hi> in pretending to <hi>Pray by the Spirit;</hi> how they are <hi>meer Deceivers, and Men-pleaſers</hi> in it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Chap. I. Shewing <hi>Jo. Bunyan's Imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> not only in urging Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſuppreſſing ſo much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as makes againſt him, as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. which is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd, and Vindicated from the falſe Gloſſes he puts upon it, and turned full upon him; but alſo in his <hi>intolerable Pride, impudent Calumnies, and railing Accuſations</hi> againſt us;
<pb facs="tcp:102911:3"/>and a Queſtion is asked; <hi>How poor Creatures ſhall Pray in their Families, who have not this pretended Gift of Prayer?</hi> Which his <hi>Party</hi> are deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Anſwer ſome <hi>better way,</hi> than by bidding them to <hi>Groan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. II. Returning an Anſwer to his Objections againſt the <hi>Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Book,</hi> and clearing it from the <hi>Imputation of Popery,</hi> there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereof in it, but <hi>Compoſed by Proteſtant Martyrs;</hi> together with ſundry Scripture Authorities, for the Lawfulneſs of Forms of Prayer, and our Obſervation of <hi>Chriſtmas, Eaſter, and other Holy Days,</hi> in Memory of the Saints.</item>
               <item>Chap. III. Concerning his evaſive An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to our Saviour's Command for the uſe of the Lord's Prayer, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.2. which is briefly Explain'd and Confirm'd, with ſome Reflections on his <hi>Rules</hi> for Prayer, as alſo on the <hi>Presbyterian Directory,</hi> wherein, they as much limit the Spirit, as we do by a Form; as alſo concerning the falſeneſs of his Aſſertion; <hi>That none
<pb facs="tcp:102911:3"/>but Saints ought to ſay the Lord's Prayer,</hi> from the known Examples of the <hi>Prodigal Son,</hi> and <hi>Rich Man,</hi> the <hi>one calling God,</hi> and <hi>the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Father,</hi> and from that Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which God bears to us by <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> and <hi>Redemption,</hi> he being on both accounts, the <hi>Father of all Men.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. IV. Of the Anabaptiſts <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Spirit and Cruelty</hi> towards other Proteſtants, and particularly towards <hi>King</hi> Charles <hi>the Martyr, and his Loyal Subjects;</hi> and their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizing ſuch Perſecutors for Saints and Martyrs, contrary to the Practice of thoſe that deſerved and had that Name among the Primitive Chriſtians, whoſe only Weapons were Prayers and Tears;</hi> and of that Perſecuting Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the ſolemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, where they are <hi>Sworn to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate us.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. V. Of ſome Texts of Scripture, <hi>Jo. Bunyan</hi> brings for the Prohibition of the Common Prayer Book, which are all ſhewn to prove no ſuch thing,
<pb facs="tcp:102911:4"/>but rather the Lawfulneſs of uſing it.</item>
               <item>Chap. VI. Of two other Places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which he produceth to the ſame purpoſe, as <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. which rightly Explain'd, do both conclude againſt him, and for the Lawfulneſs of Praying by a Form.</item>
               <item>Chap. VII. Of his two Scripture Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, for Praying by the Spirit, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. ſhewing them to be impertinently Alleged, and clearing them from the <hi>ſilly Expoſition and Paraphraſe</hi> he makes upon them; and proving, that one at leaſt, if not both of them, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Forms of Prayer, and overthrow his Pretences of Praying by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</item>
               <item>Chap. VIII. Of two plain Proofs, that <hi>Jo. Bunyan</hi> and his Party, have not the Spirit which they pretend to; <hi>viz.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>The Schiſm which they have made, and continue in the Church, with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions they have rais'd and carryed on againſt the State. 2dly. The ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and unchriſtian Language</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:102911:4"/>utter againſt us, which is exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in ſome farther Inſtances than were given in the firſt Chapter.</item>
               <item>Chap. IX. Of another Proof to the ſame purpoſe, from his <hi>evil Counſel</hi> about the Education of Children, whom he would rather have to live <hi>without Praying at all,</hi> than to be taught it <hi>by any Form whatſoever,</hi> which does not <hi>ſavour of the Spirit of God;</hi> no more does his <hi>Beaſtly Expreſſion,</hi> in calling this, a <hi>Nuzzling them up in a Form.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chap. X. An Apology for the Author, leaſt his Book be Condemned, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing the Holy Spirit; and the <hi>Aſſiſtance which he affords,</hi> is farther Explained and Stated, and Proved not to conſiſt in the <hi>Groans, or</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore <hi>Effuſions of Men,</hi> but in <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Motions within us, and the fervent Deſires of the Heart; the Life and Soul of Prayer, being Faith, Hope, and Charity;</hi> and ſuch an Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit, our Church admits, and teacheth us to Pray for.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:102911:5"/>
            <p>The Concluſion. An <hi>Addreſs</hi> to all the Members of our <hi>Orthodox Church of</hi> England, <hi>not only to Pray, but alſo to Live according to the Common Prayer Book, even a Godly, Righteous, and Sober Life, to the Glory of God's holy Name.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102911:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>BEing ſenſible, that ſome Men will cenſure, me for entring the Liſts with <hi>ſuch a Combatant,</hi> where it will be no Credit to Conquer, but a mighty Diſgrace to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, I think my ſelf obliged to give this Account of the <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking,</hi> to reconcile the Reader, to
<pb facs="tcp:102911:6"/>what I have hereafter Written, leaſt otherwiſe, looking only on the Title-Page, he ſhould grow Angry, and Impatient, and throw away the Book.</p>
            <p>The Diſcourſe I here Anſwer, was ſent me from an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> of my Pariſh, and (as I have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) by the Order and Direction, of one of their <hi>Teachers,</hi> as a <hi>choice Piece,</hi> which might take me off from the <hi>uſe of the Common Prayer Book</hi> (whoſe <hi>Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Service, I wiſh were conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offer'd up entire in all other Families as well as mine, when it cannot be perform'd in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> and I am confident, they will receive no <hi>little Comfort</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:102911:6"/>in ſo doing) but having read it over, I found ſo much <hi>Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Wreſting, and Miſ-applying of Scripture,</hi> almoſt in every Page, and ſo little Reaſon and Truth in any thing he ſaid; I once thought his reviling, impertinent Diſcourſe unworthy of any other Anſwer, but what the Archangel returned to Satan, <hi>Jud. 9. The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke thee,</hi> Bunyan: But when I conſidered the <hi>high Value</hi> the <hi>whole Party</hi> ſet upon ſuch <hi>ſlight ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pamphlets;</hi> how this was <hi>Bequeathed</hi> as a <hi>Legacy,</hi> by the <hi>laſt Will and Teſtament</hi> of one of them, to a ſurviving Friend, to convince the World, <hi>That whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Living or Dying, they have no Charity for us;</hi> and how
<pb facs="tcp:102911:7"/>they are contented, that themſelves and <hi>ſubtle Books,</hi> ſhould be let alone, to <hi>Creep into Houſes, and lead ſilly Women,</hi> (I may add <hi>Men too</hi>) <hi>Captive,</hi> (who are ſooner caught and ſeduc'd, with crafty and incoherent Reaſoning, than with cloſe and ſound Arguments) and when they have gain'd them for <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and drawn them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>wild Mazes</hi> of their nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Errors, 'tis very hard to reduce and bring them back into the way of Truth: On all theſe Accounts, I judged it needful to wipe off the <hi>ſoul Aſperſions</hi> he caſts on our <hi>Common Prayer Book,</hi> and all that uſe it, and to Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and Confute his <hi>Pretences to Pray by the Spirit, as St.</hi> Paul
<pb facs="tcp:102911:7"/>
               <hi>did;</hi> which I have done in the <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe,</hi> wherein I have ſhewn, the <hi>Vanity and Sophiſtry</hi> of all his Arguments for himſelf, and againſt us, eſpecially thoſe that are fetcht from Scripture, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned them with their <hi>genuine Force,</hi> upon his <hi>own Head;</hi> I have there alſo Proved, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit does not now <hi>Invent and Dictate the very Words of our Prayers,</hi> as they pretend he does, tho' all their Pretences of this Nature, are meer <hi>Cant,</hi> and a <hi>Device</hi> how to <hi>pleaſe Men more than God,</hi> for <hi>Almighty God, who is the ſame Yeſterday, to Day, and for Ever, is not delighted with Novelty, Variety, and change of Words;</hi> and therefore our Lord Jeſus, in
<pb facs="tcp:102911:8"/>his laſt Agony, Prayed <hi>Thrice</hi> in the ſame Words, <hi>Mat. 26.44.</hi> and without doubt, in the uſe of that ſhort <hi>pithy Form,</hi> (for ſo it was to him, having ſaid it <hi>Twice</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) he was as fervent in his Deſires the <hi>Third time</hi> as he was at <hi>Firſt;</hi> 'tis <hi>mortal Man</hi> only, (who <hi>has itching Ears</hi>) that loves to have them <hi>Tickled</hi> with <hi>new Expreſſions;</hi> and in Complyance with this vain Humour, I fear it is, that theſe Men decry all <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Forms,</hi> even <hi>that of Chriſt's own Compoſing,</hi> and ſet up their <hi>Praying by the Spirit;</hi> which yet is but a <hi>meer Artifice,</hi> the <hi>effect of a good Memory, and great Confidence;</hi> and to caſt a <hi>Miſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Peoples Eyes,</hi> they <hi>Chop
<pb facs="tcp:102911:8"/>and Change the very ſame Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, beginning where they end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ending where they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Dexterous manner,</hi> that their ignorant Hearers perceive it not, but believe their Prayers are always <hi>New,</hi> and the <hi>Product of the Spirit;</hi> but more <hi>knowing Perſons,</hi> (who often hear them) <hi>diſcover the Cheat,</hi> and that they are the <hi>very ſame Prayers ſtill,</hi> with <hi>ſome little Alterations,</hi> and ſo they continue in the uſe of <hi>Forms themſelves,</hi> whilſt yet, they are ſo Preſumptuous, as to Condemn it in others for an <hi>Antichriſtian Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more, but refer the Reader to the ſerious Peruſal of the following Diſcourſe, where I
<pb facs="tcp:102911:9"/>ſhall leave him to determine how well or ill I have Managed it, thinking it no leſs vain than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, to attempt the Byaſing of his Judgment, by a <hi>Complement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Preface;</hi> only, I Pray a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing may attend him, in the judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reading what, I aſſure him, I have Written for no other end, but God's Glory, and his Churches good; and ſo I bid him heartily Farewel.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102911:9"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF THE LITURGY Againſt the <hi>Diſſenters, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>'TIS Obſervable of <hi>Satan</hi> that when he temped our bleſſed Saviour to throw himſelf Headlong from the Pinacle of the Temple, he urges <hi>Pſalm</hi> 91.11, 12. <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thee; and in their Hands they ſhall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102911:10"/>bear thee up, leſt at any time thou daſh thy Foot againſt a Stone;</hi> but the Devil leaves out part of the Verſe which made againſt him, <hi>To keep thee in all thy ways,</hi> i. e. the ways of God, but not in all <hi>thy wandrings from them;</hi> wherein it would have been Preſumption to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the Divine protection; the like Courſe does <hi>John Bunyan</hi> take, when he urges 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. <hi>I will pray with the Spirit, and I will pray with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding alſo;</hi> he omits the later part of the Verſe, <hi>I will ſing with the Spirit, and I will ſing with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo;</hi> and he does not only omit this in the Title Page, but in ſix or ſeven Repetitions af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, which no doubt was deſignedly done, becauſe if he had once mentioned this, it would have been a plain and full Confutation of his Argument deduced from the former part of the Verſe, and indeed of his whole Book; for if we may Sing with the Spirit, when we have a form of Words and a Tune alſo to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, which is ſuppoſed and allowed in our preſent Practice of Pſalmody, Why may we not as well Pray with the Spirit
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102911:10"/>when we have a form of Words before us? Is there not the ſame Reaſon for Praying as for Singing with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, when both are done in a form of ſound Words? This is ſuch a convinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proof of the lawfulneſs of Forms of Prayer, and that thoſe who devoutly uſe them, may be aſſiſted by the Spirit of God, that it overthrows all his Cavils and Exceptions againſt them, and ſtrikes his Cauſe dead; thus the Author <hi>ſtumbles</hi> in the <hi>Threſhold,</hi> and diſcovers the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Foot</hi> in the very entrance, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in every Page of his Book, as is evident from his intolerable Pride and uncharitableneſs which he ſhews there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; of which I ſhall give you a taſte, for to mentionall would be to Tranſcribe his whole Diſcourſe, Page 14 he ſays, <hi>That Ignorance, Profaneſs and the Spirit of Envy reigns in the Hearts of thoſe Men that are ſo hot for Forms of Prayers, &amp;c. ſcarce one in Forty of them knows what 'tis to be born again, to have Communion with the Father through the Son, &amp;c. they ſtill live Curſed, Drunken, Whoriſh and Abominable Lives, full of Malice, Envy, Decit, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102911:11"/>of the dear Children of God; Oh what a dreadful after-clap is coming upon them! Which all their Hypocritical aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelves together with all their Prayers ſhall never be able to help them againſt, or ſhelter them from,</hi> and p. 43, 44. he ſays, <hi>Every curſed Whoremaſter, Theif, and Drunkard, Swearer and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured Perſon, they that have not only been ſuch in times paſt, but are even ſo ſtill, theſe I ſay, by ſome, muſt be counted the only ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men, and all becauſe with their Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Throats, and Hypocritical Hearts, they will come to Church and ſay,</hi> Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>Nay farther, theſe Men, tho' every time they ſay to God,</hi> Our Father, <hi>do moſt abominably Blaſpeme, yet they muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd thus to do;</hi> and p. 45, 46. ſays he, <hi>Give me leave to Reaſon with thee thou blind ignorant Sot; it may be thy great Prayer is to ſay,</hi> Our Father which art in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c. Is not the Devil thy Father? And dareſt thou ſay to God,</hi> Our Father, <hi>&amp;c. But as the Devil preſented himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sons of God,</hi> Job 1. <hi>when they were to preſent themſelves before the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even our Father, ſo is it now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102911:11"/>the Saints are commanded to ſay our Father, therefore all the blind ignorant Rabble in the World, they muſt alſo uſe the ſame Words,</hi> Our Father.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of the <hi>baſe, ſcurrilous</hi> and <hi>unchriſtian Reflections</hi> he every where beſtows on the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> without excepting any out of that number, making them, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms himſelf, and his holy Brethren were accounted in his time, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. <hi>As the filth of the World, and the off-ſcouring of all things unto this day;</hi> and I appeal to all ſober and good Men, whether this be not the Language of a pround and uncharitable Spirit, <hi>and of a Tongue ſet on fire of Hell?</hi> Jam. 3.6. and as his Malice and Uncharitableneſs appears in calling <hi>us the Children of the Devil,</hi> ſo does his Pride alſo, in calling <hi>himſelf and his Party Saints,</hi> as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt from the laſt Paſſage I quoted out of him, <hi>Before the Father, even our Father; to whom the Saints,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſuch as themſelves, may thus addreſs, but none of the blind ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Sots,</hi> (as we are) <hi>of the World beſides.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102911:12"/>
               <p>Page 73, he ſtarts a Queſtion, <hi>What would you have us poor Creatures to do that cannot tell how to Pray?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Where, before I give you his Anſwer, I cannot chooſe but take notice again of the ſubtilty of the Man, in ſuppreſſing ſo much of the Objection, as would have made it unanſwerable, if he had but fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propoſed it, and that is this; <hi>How ſhall we poor Creatures Pray in our reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Families, ſince we have not the Gift of Prayer, which you and others pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to? If it be an evil thing to make uſe of Forms, to have Prayerleſs Families is much worſe, and that ours muſt be, if we are denied ſuch needful helps;</hi> Now what would <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſay to this <hi>untoward Objection?</hi> Wou'd they adviſe theſe poor Creatures, as I am credibly inform'd, a <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> did a Neighbour of his, when he was deſired to compoſe a form of Prayers for him to uſe in his Family, <hi>viz. that he had better ſit down and Groan,</hi> I ſuppoſe by what follows in my Author, that ſuch poor Creatures muſt <hi>kneel down,</hi> for that is a more humble poſture than ſitting, <hi>and groan awhile,</hi> and that muſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102911:12"/>for as good a <hi>Family Prayer,</hi> as if he had ſaid one out of the <hi>Practice of Piety;</hi> but alas! This will not ſerve the turn, for what <hi>Edification</hi> is this to the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, altho' they ſhould all <hi>groan</hi> with him? What <hi>reaſonable Service</hi> is <hi>this</hi> to preſent to Almighty God? or, Wherein is <hi>this</hi> better than the <hi>Quakers Silent-Meetings?</hi> And if <hi>Groaning</hi> with ones Family, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Praying with them be Abſurd and Ridiculous, I would fain know what other courſe ſuch ignorant Maſters muſt Steer, who have not this pretended gift of Prayer? Certainly there is no other Remedy for them but to uſe the help of ſome <hi>Pious Form,</hi> in Praying with their Family, or elſe they muſt forbear Praying with them, till they have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained this pretended Gift, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may not be ſo long as they live; and then they muſt never Pray with them at all; and ſo fall under the Curſe denounced againſt ſuch <hi>Families as call not on the name of the Lord,</hi> Jer. 10.25. <hi>Where thoſe that cannot pray in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies without it, and yet deſpiſe the aſſiſtance of a Form, have a form of Prayer made to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102911:13"/>their Hands, but it is a dreadful one, that Woes and Vengeance in it; which I deſire all concern'd therein ſeriouſly to conſider, leſt it fall one day upon their Guilty Heads;</hi> But in Anſwer to this Query, as our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary has <hi>mollified it,</hi> what would you have us poor Creatures do, that cannot tell how to Pray <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he ſay, <hi>poor Heart! Thou canſt not, (thou complaineſt) Pray; canſt thou ſee thy Miſery? Hath God ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee that thou art by Nature under the curſe of his Law? If ſo, do not miſtake, I know thou doſt Groan, and that moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly; I am perſwaded thou canst ſcarely be found doing any thing in thy Calling but Prayer breaks from thy Heart; Have not thy Groans gone up to Heaven from every corner of thy Houſe? I know 'tis thus, and ſo alſo doth thine own ſorrowful Heart Witneſs thy Tears, thy forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Calling,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is not thy Heart ſo full of deſires after the things of another World, that many times thou doſt forget the things of this World?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What <hi>abominable Pride and fulſome Flattery is this? He is perſwaded of his own Party</hi> that Prayer breaks from their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102911:13"/>Heart in every thing they are doing, tho' he does not hear them utter one Word to that purpoſe; he <hi>knows</hi> they groan moſt bitterly in every corner of their Houſe, as if he were by, and heard, and ſaw, and followed theſe poor Creatures from one Room to another; he has the Confidence to ſay more than once; <hi>I know 'tis thus with them;</hi> but when he is ſpeaking <hi>of ſome of our People,</hi> he has the impudence to ſay, <hi>ſcarce one in Forty of them knows what 'tis to be born again, and to have Communion with God,</hi> and this he is as ſure of as he is of the <hi>Heart breaking</hi> Prayers and <hi>bitter Groans</hi> of his own dear Brethren, and as if he had ſeen and read the <hi>Book of Life. John Bunyan</hi> can tell how <hi>few</hi> of us, <hi>ſcarce one in Forty,</hi> and how <hi>many</hi> of them, yea, <hi>all his own poor Creatures have every one of their Names</hi> written therein; and he lays down <hi>one Mark</hi> whereby to diſcern it, <hi>viz.</hi> that their Hearts is ſo full of Deſire after the the things of another World, that they forget many times the things of This, <hi>tho this is a very fallible one,</hi> as is clear from <hi>Balaam,</hi> who had ſometimes ſuch
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102911:14"/>eager Deſires as theſe, <hi>Let me Die the Death of the Righteous, and let my last End be like his,</hi> Num. 23.10. yea he was a Prophet, and had his Viſions and Trances, wherein without doubt he thought and ſpake ſo much of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World, that he ſometimes quite forgot this; and yet notwithſtanding his <hi>Gift of Prophecy,</hi> (which ſurely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall'd if not exceeded <hi>Jo. Bunyans Gift of Prayer</hi>) notwithſtanding his <hi>Raptures, Revelations, and Heavenly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,</hi> Balaam was a very <hi>wicked Man,</hi> giving that pernicious Council to the <hi>Moabites</hi> to ſeduce the <hi>Iſraelites to</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, by the Temptations of their Beautiful Women, <hi>Num.</hi> 31.16. <hi>he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo loved the Wages of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> and is Branded for his Iniquity in ſeveral places of the Old and New Teſtament, and in this evil and wretched Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he lived, and ſo in all likelihood he dyed, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 13.22. And this I the rather mention to ſhew that for all their Pretences <hi>to Pray by the Spirit, and to other extraordinary Gifts, this Man and his Party, may be as bad as</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102911:14"/>Balaam was; but God forbid, I ſhould think ſo of all of them, and be ſo uncharitable to them, as they are to us; I hope better things of the worſt among them, but I ſpeak this to prove that if they had <hi>greater Gifts</hi> than they pretend to, they may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, be very <hi>wicked Men,</hi> for ſo was <hi>Balaam,</hi> and ſo was <hi>O. Cromwel,</hi> ſo was Major <hi>Weir</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and ſo were ſome <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Wizards,</hi> who could all <hi>Pray in a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful manner,</hi> and were believed by their Followers, to <hi>Pray by the Spirit,</hi> and far more <hi>Powerfully</hi> too than any <hi>Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker Preacher of this Age;</hi> for we muſt carefully diſtinguiſh between the <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Gifts,</hi> and <hi>ſaving Graces of the Spirit, wicked Men</hi> may, and ſometimes have the <hi>former,</hi> but the <hi>latter</hi> fall to the Share of none but <hi>good Men;</hi> and the <hi>Praying with the Spirit,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. was ſuch an <hi>extraordinary</hi> and <hi>miraculous Gift,</hi> it was Praying in an <hi>unknown Tongue,</hi> in ſuch a Language as a Man had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver learnt, and neither the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102911:15"/>nor perhaps himſelf underſtood, tho he cou'd ſpeak it, for <hi>ver.</hi> 14. he ſays, <hi>If I Pray in an unknown Tongue,</hi> (which in the next <hi>verſe</hi> he calls a <hi>Praying with the Spirit) my Spirit Prayeth but my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful,</hi> being not able to Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret what he ſaid, which was another extraordinary Gift of the Spirit, and which he that had the Gift of Tongues ſometimes wanted; and therefore the Apoſtle intimates in this place, that there may be a ſeparation between them, between <hi>Praying with the Spirit, and Praying with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and when there is, the latter is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the former; <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>in the Church I had rather ſpeak five words with my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, that by my Voice I might Teach others, than Ten thouſand words in an unknown Tongue. i. e.</hi> in the Spirit which beſtowed that Gift; ſo that in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Judgment, <hi>Praying with the Spirit, is not always to the Edification of the Church, not always performed with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding:</hi> And ſo much my Author owns, p. 58.59. <hi>This
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102911:15"/>diſtinction was occaſioned through the</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians <hi>not obſerving, that it was their Duty to do what they did to the Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of themſelves and others too, whereas they did it for their own Commendations, ſo I judge, for many of them having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gifts, as to ſpeak with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Tongues, therefore they were more for thoſe mighty Gifts, than they were for the Edifying of their Brethren, which was the cauſe that</hi> Paul <hi>wrote this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to them, to let them underſtand, that tho' extraordinary Gifts were excellent, yet to do what they did was more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, for</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>If I Pray in an unknown Tongue, my Spirit Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is unfruitful, and alſo the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of others; therefore I will Pray with the Spirit and I will Pray with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo;</hi> but (as I obſerv'd in the beginning of this Chapter) <hi>he ſtops ſhort here,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding (which I ſhall therefore add) <hi>I will Sing with the Spirit and I will Sing with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo;</hi> the plain meaning of which Phraſe, is this, <hi>viz.</hi> that in the Apoſtles Days,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102911:16"/>ſome were enabled by a miraculous Gift of the Spirit, not only to Pray in an <hi>unknown Tongue,</hi> but alſo to Sing in an unknown <hi>Pſalm</hi> or <hi>Hymn,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears farther from <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>When ye come together, every one of you hath a Pſalm, hath a Tongue,</hi> &amp;c. both theſe were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary and miraculous Gifts, by the Confeſſion of our <hi>Adverſary,</hi> and he may as well pretend to <hi>Sing as Pray</hi> extempore <hi>from this Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> but unleſs he can <hi>Sing and Pray in an unknown Tongue,</hi> he doth not <hi>Sing and Pray as St.</hi> Paul <hi>and the</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians <hi>did;</hi> and if notwithſtanding this, devout Chriſtians may Compoſe Spiritual Songs and Hymns, and Sing them according to the Rules of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Notes, and yet all that while be aſſiſted by the Spirit; ſo may they alſo Compoſe Prayers and Praiſes before-hand, and read them in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, who are to join with them therein, and yet all that time be aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame Spirit, <hi>for Praying and Singing with the Spirit; are expreſſed,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102911:16"/>(as<note n="*">Diſcourſe of <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> Prayer p. 13.</note> Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) <hi>in the ſame Place, in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to the ſame end, and I know no Reaſon why there ſhould be differing Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes put upon them to ſerve purpoſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>HAving clear'd the Scope and Meaning of this <hi>mangled, divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and abuſed Text, and detected the</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors <hi>Pride in Sainting himſelf, and his own Party, and his Diabolical Slanders, in making Devils Incarnate of us;</hi> I ſhall next, conſider the <hi>malicious Reflections</hi> he caſts on our Churches <hi>Liturgy,</hi> in the Proſecution of his Diſcourſe: Page 11. he ſays, <hi>Our Common Prayer Book is taken out of the Papiſtical Maſs Book, being the Scraps and Devices of ſome Popes, ſome Friars, and I wot not what;</hi> and this he repeats Page 29. Paul <hi>and his Companions, were as able to have made a Common Prayer Book, as any Pope or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and could as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102911:17"/>well have made a Common Prayer Book, as thoſe who first Compoſed this,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But I have theſe things to offer, to ſhew the <hi>Falſeneſs,</hi> and <hi>Senſeleſsneſs</hi> of ſuch Suggeſtions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1ſt.</hi> That our Common Prayer Book was not <hi>Compiled by any Pope or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of</hi> Rome, but by ſome <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Divines, who ſuffer'd Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for the Proteſtant Religion, Sealing it with their Blood; and how can that ſavour of Popery, that was the joint and unanimous Work of Proteſtant Martyrs, who, without doubt were aſſiſted therein, with the ſame Holy Spirit that enabled them to reſiſt unto Blood? and one of them</hi> (<note n="*">See <hi>Fox's Martyrol.</hi> p. 1524. They with weeping Eyes Prayed together, and Kiſſed one another, and he gave unto her a Book of the Church Service ſet out by K. <hi>Edward,</hi> which in the time of his Impriſonment he daily uſed.</note> 
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Rowland Taylor) <hi>made uſe of the Common Prayer Book when he lay in Priſon, and a little before his Martyrdom, commended it to his Wife, as the last Token of his Love.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2d.</hi> If it were true, that the Common Prayer Book were taken out of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102911:17"/>Maſs, that is no Proof of its Unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if there be nothing elſe Sinful in it, the Papiſts uſing ſome ſuch Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as we do, does not render them Unlawful: <hi>They uſe to anoint Sick and Dying Perſons with Oyl, and ſo do the Anabaptiſts;</hi> and when urg'd with this, that theirs is a Popiſh Practice, their Anſwer is, that 'tis never the worſe for all that, if it be according to the Word of God; and may not we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the ſame Anſwer? <hi>That our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are never the worſe, tho' ſome of them ſhou'd be found (yet in another Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) in the Maſs Book, ſo long as they are agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>able to the Holy Scriptures, and purſuant to thoſe excellent Forms Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded there.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3dly.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are ſo far from <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>favouring</hi> the Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that the firſt thing they did after Queen <hi>Mary</hi> aſcended the Throne, was to <hi>aboliſh and cast it out of the Church,</hi> which they would never have done, if they had thought it conducing to the advancement of their Cauſe; but <hi>they knew it was the best Defence and Buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102911:18"/>we have against Popery, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore demoliſhed and took it away, and ſo did the Diſſenters again, in the</hi> Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellian <hi>Days,</hi> and we may on their own grounds, conclude them to be <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> becauſe they ſhewed the ſame <hi>Enmity and Spight to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book, and with diſdain laid it aſide, as the Papiſts had done before;</hi> and if theſe Men are never the worſe for doing the <hi>ſame things</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did; Why is our Common Prayer Book the worſe, for having <hi>ſome things</hi> in it, which the <hi>Maſs Book has?</hi> Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if it be conſider'd, that all their Prayers are in <hi>Latin,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage <hi>unknown</hi> to the common People; all our Prayers are in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which is our <hi>Mother Tongue,</hi> and underſtood by the Vulgar; moſt of their Prayers are preſented to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> and to other <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels; all our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> are offer'd up <hi>to God, through the Mediation of Jeſus Christ;</hi> and with how <hi>many and</hi> (to ſay no worſe) <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome Ceremonies, Baptiſm and the Lords Supper is Adminiſtred among them?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102911:18"/>And with how few and Significant ones thoſe Sacraments are Celebrated by us;</hi> (all which, make a <hi>vaſt Difference,</hi> between the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> and <hi>Maſs Book</hi>) any one will eaſily find, that has leiſure and opportunity to Compare them both together.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4ly.</hi> How does <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> know that St. <hi>Paul</hi> never compoſed a Form of Prayer? The <hi>ſound Words</hi> he commands <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>hold faſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. might (for ought he can prove to the contrary) be ſuch a <hi>Form;</hi> himſelf allows the <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> which the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. to have reſpect to a Form of Prayer, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter, and is there not as good reaſon that this <hi>Form of ſound Words</hi> ſhould likewiſe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard Prayer?</hi> And if it does, we may thence infer, that St. <hi>Paul made ſuch a Form for the Church, and commanded</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy <hi>to hold faſt the ſame by uſing it therein;</hi> however this be, we may be ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſed a Form of Prayer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, even that of Chriſt's own compoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. when ye pray ſay, <hi>our Father,</hi> &amp;c. and he taught others to uſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102911:19"/>it alſo; or elſe he could not <hi>have kept a Conſcience void of Offence towards God and towards Man, neither would he have declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto his People the whole Council of God, as he proteſts he had done,</hi> Acts 20.27. and Chap. 24.16. and if St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles uſed no other Form of Prayer, it was becauſe they were <hi>aſſiſted by the immediate inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, and had miraculous Gifts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them,</hi> ſuch as <hi>the gift of Tongues, of Propheſie, of Healing,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo <hi>did not ſtand in need of it; and let</hi> John Bunyan <hi>and his Party prove they have the like wonderful Gifts, and can work the like ſtupendious Miracles, and they ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with in the uſe of the Common Prayer Book;</hi> but if <hi>none</hi> of thoſe <hi>extraordinary Gifts and Miracles</hi> can be truly <hi>pretended to by them,</hi> then I think they <hi>need the help of ſuch a Form of ſound Words as well as we; and this has been the conſtant Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of God in all Ages ſince thoſe Miracles ceaſed; and therefore did ſhe at firſt eſtabliſh Liturgies, and has always uſed them, if not in, at leaſt ever ſince the Apoſtles Days.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:102911:19"/>
               <p>Page 31 our Author is very witty and ſays, <hi>But here the wiſe Men of our Days are ſo well skill'd, as that they have both the Matter and Manner of their Prayers at their Fingers end; ſetting ſuch a Prayer for ſuch a Day, and that twenty Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it comes, one for</hi> Chriſtmas, <hi>another for</hi> Eaſter, <hi>and ſix Days after that; they have alſo bounded how many Syllables muſt be ſaid in every one of them at their publick Exerciſes; for each Saints Day alſo they have them ready for the Generations yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born to ſay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this <hi>(which is meer Banter)</hi> muſt paſs for an invincible Argument to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw our <hi>whole Liturgy</hi> at once, and every <hi>Collect</hi> therein; but ſuch as it is we will examine it, and ſhew the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity and folly of it.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> This Man does not ſhew his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in pretending we make Prayers for certain Days <hi>twenty Years before</hi> they come; ſince <hi>thoſe very Days happen all within the compaſs of One Year,</hi> and therefore there cannot be the diſtance of twenty Years between them, and the making ſuch particular Prayers; and if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102911:20"/>it be ſaid that theſe Prayers are repeated for more than twenty Years one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; we may anſwer, there is good reaſon for it, <hi>that as often as ſuch ſolemn times return, we ſhould ſuit our publick Prayers and Praiſes according to ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Occaſions, having the Example of God himſelf, and his Servant</hi> Moſes, <hi>to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our Practice;</hi> for by the <hi>Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment,</hi> the Prieſts under the Law, were confin'd to a <hi>Form of Words</hi> in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the People, which they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to pronounce when they diſmiſſed the Aſſembly; <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.22, 23, 24, 25, 26. <hi>the Lord ſpake unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>ſaying, ſpeak unto</hi> Aaron <hi>and his Sons, ſaying, on this wiſe ye ſhall bleſs the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſaying unto them; the Lord bleſs thee, and keep thee; the Lord make his Face to ſhine upon thee; and be gracious unto thee; the Lord lift up his Countenance upon thee, and give thee Peace; in which one Bleſſing, wherein the name of Jehovah or Lord is thrice repeated, we are taught the great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of our Chriſtian Faith, even the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, or the three Perſons and one God, it being the peculiar property of God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102911:20"/>the Father to bleſs and keep us, of God the Son to be gracious unto us, and of God the Holy Ghoſt to give us Peace,</hi> as<note n="*">See his Com. on <hi>Num.</hi> pag. 109.</note> Dr. <hi>Patrick</hi> has obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; to the like form of Words was <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf confin'd as often as the Ark moved and reſted in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Numb.</hi> 10.35, 36. <hi>When the Ark ſet forward,</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid, riſe up O Lord, and let thine Enemies be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and let them that hate thee flee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; and when the Ark reſted he ſaid, return O Lord to the many thouſands of</hi> Iſrael; and by the <hi>ſame divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People were obliged to <hi>a ſet form</hi> of Words in praying to God, and praiſing his Name, when they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd <hi>their firſt Fruits,</hi> Deut. 26.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſpeak and ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord thy God, a</hi> Syrian <hi>ready to periſh was my Father, and he went down into</hi> Egypt, <hi>and ſojourned there with a few, and became there a Nation great, mighty, and populous; and the</hi> Egyptians <hi>evil entreated us, and afflicted us, and laid upon us hard Bondage; and when we cried unto the Lord God of our Fathers, the Lord
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102911:21"/>heard our Voice, and looked on our Afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and our Labour and our Oppreſſion; and the Lord brought us forth out of</hi> Egypt <hi>with a mighty Hand, and out ſtretched arm, and with great terribleneſs, and with Signs and with Wonders, and he hath brought us unto this Place, and hath given us this Land, even a Land that floweth with Milk and Honey, and now behold I have brought the firſt Fruits of the Land which thou, O Lord, haſt given me.</hi> The like Form of Words were they obliged to uſe in the Offering of their Tythes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.13, 14, 15. <hi>Thou ſhall ſay before the Lord thy God, I have brought away the hallowed things out of my Houſe, and alſo have given them unto the</hi> Levite, <hi>and unto the Stranger, to the Fatherleſs and to the Widow, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all thy Commandments which thou haſt commanded; I have not tranſgreſſed thy Commandments, neither have I forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten them; I have not eaten thereof in my Mourning; neither have I taken ought thereof for any unclean uſe, nor given ought thereof for the Dead; but I have harkened to the Voice of the Lord my God, and have done according to all that thou haſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102911:21"/>commanded me; look down from thy holy Habitation from Heaven, and bleſs thy People</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Land which thou haſt given us, as thou ſweareſt unto our Fathers, a Land that floweth with Milk and Honey;</hi> And both theſe Forms of Prayer and Thankſgiving, were the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People conſtantly to obſerve twice every Year in all ſucceeding Generations when they offer'd their <hi>firſt Fruits</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> before the Lord; but according to <hi>John Bunyan's bantering way</hi> he would <hi>expoſe them thus; The Wiſe Men of</hi> Moſes <hi>his Days, with himſelf the Prieſts and People, were ſo well skill'd, that they had both the matter and the manner of their Prayers at their Fingers end, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a Prayer for ſuch a Day, and that twenty Years before it comes, one for the Day wherein they Offered their First-fruits, another for the Day wherein they Offered their Tythes; they have alſo bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how many Syllables must be ſaid in every one of their Prayers, at their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Exerciſes, for each of theſe Offering Days, they have them ready for the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations yet unborn to ſay;</hi> ſo that if
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102911:22"/>there be any weight in this way of Arguing, it will caſt as much diſgrace upon the Prayers of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (which yet were Dictated and Directed by the <hi>infinite Wiſdom of Almighty God</hi>) as upon the Prayers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which were alſo Compoſed by the ſame Spirit.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prieſts and People had not the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Holy Spirit, as we have, and therefore they were tyed to Forms, from which we are now ſet free: I Anſwer, (or rather <hi>John Bunyan</hi> does it for me, p. 53) <hi>You do not find any Words of Prayer that we read of, come out of the Mouth of</hi> Moſes, <hi>when he was going out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>Ex.</hi> 14.15. <hi>and yet he made Heaven ring again with his Cry, but it was the inexpreſſible and unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Groans and Cryings of his Soul, in and with the Spirit;</hi> And this he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats p. 75. ſo that by our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries own Confeſſion, <hi>Moſes</hi> had the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and could <hi>Pray by it,</hi> even in their Senſe as well at leaſt as any <hi>Gifted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102911:22"/>Brother</hi> of them all; and yet this very <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſometimes uſed a <hi>Form</hi> of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er himſelf, and alſo preſcribed a <hi>Form</hi> of Prayers for others, even the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prieſts and People, to be conſtantly obſerved by them on <hi>ſolemn Occaſions,</hi> and on ſuch <hi>particular Days,</hi> and <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Year.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> Thoſe <hi>two</hi> great <hi>ſolemn Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals,</hi> which my Author mentions as obſerv'd by our Church, <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> and <hi>Eaſter,</hi> have good Authority for their Obſervation, even in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for can we have better War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for our keeping <hi>Chriſtmas-Day,</hi> than the <hi>Holy Angels</hi> keeping of it in a full <hi>Quire,</hi> as they did <hi>Luke</hi> 2.13. <hi>and ſuddenly there was with the Angel</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> who brought the Shepherds the joyful News of Chriſt's Birth) <hi>a Multitude of the Heavenly Host, Praiſing God, and ſaying,</hi> (and they did it all in the <hi>ſame Form</hi>) <hi>Glory to God in the highest, and on Earth Peace, and good Will towards Men.</hi> Now, What other Reaſon can there be given, why ſo many (if not all) the Angels
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102911:23"/>ſhould be preſent on Earth at this time, and unanimouſly Worſhip God, except it were to teach us to ſet apart <hi>this Day</hi> in all future Ages, for a Day of Thankſgiving to God, for the greateſt Mercy was afforded the World ſince the Creation, even the Birth and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of the Saviour of it? Well may we keep <hi>Chriſtmaſs-Day,</hi> our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature being aſſum'd into the Godhead, and a Saviour being Born to us upon it, which is Chriſt the Lord: When the Holy Angels kept <hi>this Day,</hi> whoſe Nature he did not aſſume, and to whom he was not Born a Saviour, as he was to us.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſay no more in behalf of this great Feſtival, but Tranſcribe a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage out of the <hi>Aſſemblies Annotations</hi> on this portion of Scripture, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 13.<note n="‖">See the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations</hi> on <hi>Luke</hi> 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Thus God would</hi> (ſay they) <hi>have this publick Service</hi> (for ſo their Multitude made it) <hi>performed by all who have Knowledge of, and Interest in the Birth of Chriſt, as to manifest his Mercy and Truth, ſo to Condemn their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102911:23"/>ſtupid Ingratitude, who perverſely refuſe to joyn in this Duty; as if general Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts in Gods Word, right Reaſon, and the Examples of Men and Angels inſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Gods Spirit, choſen Witneſſes of of our Saviours Nativity, and for this ſame purpoſe ſent by God himſelf from Heaven, that they might thus Celebrate that Day; were not ſufficient Warrant to lead them to Imitation, and joining in an Holy Harmony with them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for our keeping <hi>Eaſter Day,</hi> can we have better Authority than St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Command for it? 1 <hi>Cor..</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Christ our Paſſover is Sacrificed for us, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us keep the Feast;</hi> i.e. <hi>Eaſter,</hi> which is our Chriſtian Paſſover, that comes in the room of the Jewiſh; <hi>not with the old Leaven, neither with the Leaven of Malice and Wickedneſs;</hi> which is a plain Alluſion to ſome of the Typical Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies wherewith the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> kept their Paſſover, and proves that we Chriſtians ſhould keep <hi>Eaſter</hi> with the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of thoſe Types, even the <hi>unleavened Bread of Sincerity and Truth;</hi> i. e. in a pious Preparation for, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102911:24"/>devout Participation of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in a Death to Sin, and a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to newneſs of Life.</p>
               <p>Yet beſides this Scriptural Argument, I ſhall add one Conſideration more, and that is King <hi>Charles the Martyrs Quaery</hi> propounded to the Parliaments. Commiſſioners at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> April 23. 1647.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>I deſire to be reſolved of this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p>Why the new Reformers diſcharge the keeping of <hi>Eaſter?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Reaſon of this Quaery it;</p>
                     <p>I conceive the Celebration of this Feaſt, was Inſtituted by the ſame Authority, which changed the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sabbath into the Lords Day, or Sunday; for it will not be found in Scripture, where Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day is diſcharged to be kept, or turned into the Sunday; wherefore it must be the Churches Authority that Changed the one, and Inſtituted the other; therefore my Opinion is, that thoſe who will not keep this Feast, may as well return to the Obſervation of Saturday, and refuſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102911:24"/>the weekly Sunday; when any Body can ſhew me that herein I am in an Error, I ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs and amend it; till when you know my Mind.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>C. R.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> As to the Obſervation of <hi>Saints Days,</hi> thoſe Men have no Reaſon to upbraid us with it, who every Year keep their <hi>Feſtival Days,</hi> in Memory of the <hi>Seiges, and proſperous Rebellion, they rais'd and maintain'd against their rightful Soveraign:</hi> Indeed, had they Fought for him, and been preſerv'd and deliver'd in ſo Juſt and Loyal a Cauſe, to have kept an <hi>Anniverſary Day</hi> in Remembrance of it, wou'd have been a juſtifiable Practice; and ſo it is to obſerve thoſe few <hi>Saints Days,</hi> whoſe Memory our Church requires us once a Year to Celebrate, having the like Authority in the Holy Scripture, for their continual Obſervation, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.15. <hi>Precious in the Sight of the Lord is the Death of the Saints,</hi> and 'tis the <hi>Days</hi> of their <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102911:25"/>and not of their <hi>Birth,</hi> which we Commemorate, not their <hi>firſt Days</hi> in which they were <hi>Born into the World,</hi> but the <hi>laſt Days,</hi> in which they were <hi>Born into an happy Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and on theſe Days, we do not only Bleſs God for thoſe eminent Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Graces which Shone in them, but alſo, we deſire him to enable us to follow their good Examples; that being compaſſed about with ſo great a <hi>Cloud of Witneſſes, we may run with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the Race that is ſet before us, looking unto Jeſus their Captain General, who with them has endured the Croſs, and receiv'd a Crown in Heaven;</hi> and by this means we do what we can to perpetuate their Memory on Earth, as God expects we ſhould, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.6. <hi>The Righteous ſhall be had in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Remembrance.</hi> And this the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians began, by firſt keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Day of theſe Saints Martyrdom at the very Place where they ſuffer'd; and this after Ages follow'd, by Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating it in all other Places where Chriſtianity was profeſſed; and I doubt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102911:25"/>not but it will be continued in all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages, even unto the end of the World, among all <hi>Orthodox Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>HAving in the former Chapter, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected the <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> and <hi>Fallaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> of <hi>John Bunyans</hi> Arguments, againſt <hi>Forms of Prayer,</hi> and ſhewn how they rather conclude for them, and againſt his Pretences to Pray by the Spirit: I ſhall now proceed to diſcover the <hi>Weakneſs and Folly</hi> of his Anſwer to that convincing Proof for the Lawfulneſs of Forms, even our Saviour's Command for it, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. <hi>When ye Pray, ſay our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To this he ſays, p. 80. <hi>I cannot think that Chriſt intended it as a ſtinted Form of Prayer, becauſe he lays it down diverſly:</hi> But how <hi>diverſly?</hi> Mat. 6.9. our bleſſed Lord ſays, <hi>After this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102911:26"/>manner Pray ye, Our Father.</hi> &amp;c. the plain import of which is, that this ought to be the <hi>Pattern</hi> by which we ſhou'd Compoſe all our Prayers; but leaſt his Diſciples (who had deſired their Maſter to teach them a Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as <hi>John Baptist</hi> had taught his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) ſhou'd think it well enough to have an Eye only to this <hi>Pattern</hi> in Compoſing all their Prayers by, tho' in the mean time they never made uſe of this very Form it ſelf, therefore in <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. our Saviour ſaid unto them, <hi>When ye Pray, ſay Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> do not content your ſelves to Pray after this manner, in other Prayers of your own, Compoſing them according to it; but alſo uſe this very Prayer it ſelf, together with your own of the like Nature, that putting up your Petitions to Almighty God, with a good Heart in Chriſt's own Words, ye may be ſure to be heard; and let any honeſt Chriſtian but Read and Compare theſe two Evangeliſts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this Point, and I am confident he will acknowledge, that Chriſt muſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102911:26"/>needs intend this Prayer of his <hi>ſhould it ſelf be daily uſed, and alſo the true Standard of all our Devotions;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, he muſt needs intend it for a Form, or elſe his Words and Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would not agree, which is Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to imagine.</p>
               <p>But out Author anſwers farther, p. 81. <hi>We do not find, that the Apoſtles did ever obſerve this Form as ſuch, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did they admoniſh others ſo to do; ſearch all their Epiſtles,</hi> &amp;c. But did not the Apoſtles do many things which are not written there? As St. <hi>John</hi> ſays, <hi>there are alſo many other things which Jeſus did, which are not written every one of them in the Goſpel,</hi> Joh. 21.25: For, <hi>were not all the Apoſtles Baptized?</hi> And yet we do not Read in the New Teſtament, of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of any one of them;</hi> ſo the Apoſtles might, and without doubt did make uſe of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> tho' there be no mention of it in their Epiſtles; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe how were they Faithful in keeping Chriſts Commandments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, this being one of them? <hi>When
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102911:27"/>ye Pray, ſay, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. and this doubtleſs they taught others to uſe alſo, or elſe they were not Faithful in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Chriſts Commiſſion, who at the delivery thereof, ſpeaks thus; <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.20. <hi>Go ye therefore, and Proſelyte all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost; teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have Commanded you;</hi> and this being one thing that Chriſt had Commanded them, <hi>when ye Pray, ſay Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. we cannot ſuppoſe that they fail'd to teach others to obſerve <hi>this alſo,</hi> as well as <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or any other Goſpel Duty.</p>
               <p>But after all his trifling Anſwers to this invincible Objection, <hi>Jo. Bunyan</hi> confeſſeth, p. 81. <hi>That Chriſt by theſe Words,</hi> Our Father which art in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>doth inſtruct his People, what Rules they ſhould obſerve in their Prayers to God:</hi> And if it is a <hi>Rule</hi> for all our Prayers; is not this as great a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement of the Spirit, as the limiting of it to this, or any other Form of ſound Words?</hi> This Author, p. 75. and thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102911:27"/>that made the <hi>Directory,</hi> (tho' they are Enemies to all Forms of Prayer, and therefore aboliſhed our <hi>excellent Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi>) yet lay down <hi>certain Rules,</hi> which we muſt obſerve in Praying to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God; which is indeed, <hi>to do that thing themſelves,</hi> which they <hi>condemn in us,</hi> and call a <hi>Reſtraining of the Spirit;</hi> for to dictate to the Spirit the <hi>Heads</hi> of Prayer which he muſt inſiſt upon, and leave him at liberty only in the choice of <hi>Words,</hi> is every whit as much, if not more a reſtraining of the Spirit, than only to <hi>appoint the Words,</hi> and leave him at liberty in the <hi>choice</hi> of the <hi>Senſe; the Matter of Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more conſiderable than Words, and the Senſe more valuable than Language:</hi> If therefore the Spirit muſt be left <hi>free,</hi> why do they themſelves <hi>confine him,</hi> in impoſing on him the <hi>Heads</hi> of his Prayer? <hi>As if he needed help for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,</hi> (as our<note n="*">See his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Book, p. 686.</note> Royal Martyr obſerved) <hi>tho' not for expreſſion; or as if Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter did not as much ſtint and obſtruct the Spirit, as if it were cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102911:28"/>in, and confined to fit Words, (ſo ſlight and eaſy is the Leger-de-main which will ſerve to delude the Vulgar</hi>) And from hence any one may well conclude, that theſe Men inſtead of being <hi>inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> with the Spirit of God, are <hi>poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> with the <hi>Spirit of Pride and Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity;</hi> what elſe is the meaning of their taking away the <hi>Book of Common Prayer,</hi> and yet eſtabliſhing a <hi>Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in its room, which is as much a reſtraining of the Spirit as the other? What elſe is the meaning of that Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the entrance of the <hi>Directory,</hi> p. 5? <hi>Let all enter the Aſſembly, not irreverently, but in a grave and ſeemly manner, taking their Seats or Places with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Adoration, or Bowing themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one Place or other:</hi> But that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when we enter the Church (the Place of Gods gracious and more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Preſence) we ſolemnly Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, by Bowing our Bodies and Knees before him, therefore the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters when they enter the Church will not Worſhip God at all, being <hi>requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by the <hi>Directory</hi> to take their Seats
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102911:28"/>
                  <hi>without Adoration;</hi> tho' herein they act contrary to <hi>David,</hi> who ſays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.6. <hi>O come let us Worſhip and Bow down, let us Kneel before the Lord our Maker:</hi> They act contrary to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Converts, of whom he ſays, <hi>That com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Church, they will fall down on their Face and Worſhip God,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.25. They act contrary to thoſe Pious Souls that came to Chriſt to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Cure for themſelves or Friends; who did not approach or addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him, without a ſolemn act of Adoration, they always firſt Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, by Kneeling, Bowing, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating their Bodies before him; as you may ſee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.12. And if thoſe good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple paid Chriſt's <hi>Corporeal Preſence</hi> ſo much <hi>Reverence</hi> in the Days of his <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,</hi> certainly we ought not to give his <hi>Spiritual Preſence</hi> leſs Honour in his <hi>Exaltation,</hi> ſince he is now advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Right-hand of God; but when we approach him, ſhould Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him with <hi>our Bodies,</hi> as well as <hi>Souls;</hi> but the <hi>Directory</hi> in <hi>oppoſition</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:102911:29"/>to the Practice of theſe Holy Men, Commands the People to enter the Aſſembly (where they ſuppoſe Chriſt <hi>Spiritually preſent,</hi> or elſe, <hi>What make they there?</hi>) <hi>without Adoration,</hi> or <hi>Bowing their Bodies towards one Place or other;</hi> and conſequently they muſt not Bow their Bodies or Knees to Adore God at all; for if they do ſo, it muſt be towards ſome Place, it being impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to Worſhip God with our Bodies without it</p>
               <p>But to return from the <hi>Presbyterian Directory,</hi> (whither I have a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, preſuming it would be a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Digreſſion) to our <hi>Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Director of Spiritual Prayer,</hi> John Bunyan; p. 45. 46. he affirms, <hi>That none but ſuch as are Regenerate, can tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with allowance, ſay</hi> Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet even theſe muſt go no farther, nor venture to ſay out the Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, becauſe it is a Form, and to uſe any ſuch Forms, is as bad as ſetting up, and Worſhipping <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Calves, which was downright Idolatry; and p. 110. <hi>What is this</hi> (ſays he) <hi>leſs than
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102911:29"/>that accurſed Abomination of</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>which kept many from going to</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>the Place and Way of Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment to Worſhip?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if this be leſs than <hi>Blaſpemy,</hi> I know not what can be called by that Name; for if the uſe of godly Forms of Prayer (not excepting the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> it ſelf) be as abominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Calves, then our Lord in commanding us when we Pray, to ſay, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. muſt Command the Practice of Idolatry; which is to Charge God not only <hi>Fooliſhly,</hi> but <hi>Preſumptuouſly;</hi> and in ſo doing, to fall himſelf into <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> great Sin, in deviſing another way of Praying, than that revealed in the Word of God, and in ſlighting and deſpiſing that Form of Prayer which Chriſt has given us; a Practice which we juſtly deteſt and abhor, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in our <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> we always uſe the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> and all our other Prayers are Compoſed according to this <hi>divine and admirable Pattern;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> (whoſe <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:102911:30"/>may have great Influence on the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> if it ſhould have little on <hi>John Bunyan</hi> and his <hi>Party</hi>) was ſo much for the uſe of the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> that (I am credibly inform'd) he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly concluded his own with it, and on his Death-bed, earneſtly<note n="*">See Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Funeral Sermon, by <hi>Dr. Bates.</hi>
                  </note> Recommended the like Practice to all his Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Brethren, and wondred that any of them ſhould lay aſide the <hi>Lord's Prayer;</hi> aſſuring them he always found much Comfort in the uſe of it, and his Heart raiſed and lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heaven-wards, in the frequent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition thereof; which I mention on purpoſe to ſilence the Clamours of theſe Men againſt our Church, for uſing the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> twice, and ſometimes more in our daily Devotions; for why may not our People receive as much <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Comfort</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſays he did) in ſuch Repetitions? <hi>And can a good thing be repeated too often?</hi> They ſay, it cannot, when they require their Followers to attend the Repetition of their Sermons; and I preſume, they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102911:30"/>dare not ſay that the very <hi>beſt</hi> of their <hi>Diſcourſes, are ſo good as the Lord's Prayer,</hi> or that the Words of <hi>uninſpired Men,</hi> are equal to the Words of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> beſides, the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> being delivered by the two Evangeliſts, with ſome little Alteration, the one <hi>reciting</hi> the <hi>Doxology,</hi> the other <hi>omitting</hi> it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo we repeat this Prayer <hi>once with and once without it;</hi> in the one ending thus; <hi>Deliver us from evil,</hi> Amen, as St. <hi>Luke</hi> Chap. 11.4. and in the other thus; <hi>for thine is the Kingdom, and the Power, and the Glory, for ever and ever,</hi> Amen: Our Church enjoyning all its Members to make uſe of <hi>both Forms,</hi> that none may fail to comply with our Lords Commands, who requires us to Pray <hi>thus,</hi> and <hi>after this manner;</hi> and this I think is enough to ſatisfie the Scruples of any reaſonable Perſon, that may be offended with the Repetition of the Lords Prayer in our Churches Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Jo. Bunyan</hi> cannot diſſwade Chriſtians from uſing the Lords Prayer, (and 'twill be hard to do ſo, ſo long as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102911:31"/>they find it in their Bibles) he invents ſuch ſhifts to limit and confine this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Form, that he will allow none but <hi>Saints,</hi> i. e. ſuch as <hi>himſelf</hi> and his <hi>own Party</hi> to uſe it; (tho' I believe few have ever heard it from their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) and ſometimes he will not permit the <hi>Saints themſelves</hi> to make uſe of it, as p. 41. <hi>I tell you,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>however Hypocrites may think, yet the Chriſtian that is ſo indeed,</hi> (and that ſurely muſt be one of the Saints) <hi>finds all the difficulty in this very thing, he cannot ſay God is his Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But certainly the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Pilgrims Progreſs,</hi> had here forgotten the <hi>Parable</hi> of the <hi>Prodigal Son,</hi> who before he was a <hi>Saint,</hi> and a great way off from God, and in the <hi>far Country of Sin,</hi> whither he had fled from him, he ſaid; <hi>I will ariſe and go to my Father, and will ſay unto him, Father I have ſinned against Heaven and before thee; and am no more worthy to be called thy Son.</hi> Luke 15.13. 18.20. But had <hi>Jo. Bunyan</hi> heard this Prayer, he would have <hi>School'd</hi> him thus; <hi>Thou Poor Blind Prodigal Sot;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102911:31"/>thy great Prayer is to ſay;</hi> Father I have ſinned againſt Heaven and before thee: <hi>Dost thou know the meaning of the first Word of this Prayer? Canst thou indeed with the rest of the Saints, cry</hi> Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? <hi>Art thou truely Born again? Hast thou receiv'd the Spirit of Adoption? Dost thou ſee thy ſelf in Christ? And canst thou come to God as a Member of him? Or art thou ignorant of theſe things, and yet dareſt ſay</hi> Father? <hi>Is not the Devil thy Father? And doſt thou not do the Deeds of the Fleſh? Haſt thou not been a Prodigal Spend-thrift, waſted thy Subſtance with Riotous living, and devouerd thy Eſtate among Harlots, and yet dareſt thou ſay to God,</hi> Father?</p>
               <p>Thus Rudely, Unchriſtianly, and Uncharitably, would <hi>Jo. Bunyan</hi> treat the <hi>Prodigal Son,</hi> as the <hi>elder Brother</hi> would have had him treated; but God himſelf treats him far otherwiſe; even <hi>as a dear and tender Child;</hi> for <hi>when he was yet a great way off, his Father ſaw him, and had Compaſſion on him, and ran and fell on his Neck and kiſſed him;</hi> and his Reception and Entertainment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102911:32"/>was extraordinary, <hi>ver.</hi> 22.23. The <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Pilgrims Progreſs,</hi> had likewiſe forgotten the <hi>Parable</hi> of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus;</hi> the former, tho' in Hell, call'd <hi>Abraham Father,</hi> Luke 16.24. But <hi>Jo. Bunyan</hi> wou'd for this alone, have call'd him, <hi>Damn'd Wretch,</hi> and <hi>Child of the Devil,</hi> and demanded of him, <hi>What haſt thou to do curſed Man, to call</hi> Abraham <hi>Father?</hi> But <hi>Abraham</hi> has better Language in his Mouth, and is ſo far from reproving even this Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rich man for calling him <hi>Father,</hi> that he gives him a mild Anſwer, and the Title of <hi>Son,</hi> perhaps, becauſe he was one of his Off-ſpring, tho' much degenerated from him that was the firſt <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Stock</hi> of them; <hi>Son re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things,</hi> &amp;c. In like manner the moſt wicked Perſon in the World may call God Father; he being the God and Father of all Men by <hi>Creation,</hi> who are therefore ſaid, <hi>to be all his Off-ſpring,</hi> Acts 17.28, 29. So on the Account of their <hi>natural Being,</hi> which they receiv'd from God, all Mankind
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102911:32"/>may truly call God Father; as all the Children of an earthly Parent, tho' of far different Natures and Behaviour, may yet call him their Father; 2dly. God is the Father of all Men by <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> which is univerſal, and extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all that will ſincerely accept and lay hold of it, as is clear from 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>If any man ſin, we have an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole World:</hi> So that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt dyed for all Men, even the moſt profligate Wretches in the World, or elſe they were not bound to Repent and Believe the Goſpel; for to what purpoſe ſhou'd they do either, ſince none can be ſaved, but thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed, and then all their Repentance and Faith wou'd be in vain:</hi> So that on the account of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Redemption,</hi> we may all call Almighty God <hi>Father;</hi> altho' we were never ſo wicked, even as Satans Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as this <hi>Author</hi> ſuppoſes us to be; and by conſequence, may ſafely uſe the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> without being guilty of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102911:33"/>
                  <hi>Lying</hi> or <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> altho' none of us were <hi>Saints,</hi> at leaſt not <hi>one in Forty</hi> did deſerve that Name: Indeed <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Pen</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> upbraid us for ſaying in our Prayers; <hi>Lord have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon us miſerable Sinners;</hi> and, <hi>We have erred and ſtrayed from thy Ways like loſt Sheep:</hi> And <hi>John Bunyan</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> upbraid us for ſaying, <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. So that if we ſhould hearken to theſe Men, we muſt not Pray at all, neither addreſs our ſelves to God as <hi>Saints,</hi> nor as <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> neither ſay <hi>Our Father,</hi> nor, <hi>God be merciful to me a Sinner;</hi> but the truth is, we may, and on good Grounds do ſay both, having the Examples of <hi>David</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to juſtifie our Practice, whom I preſume our <hi>Author</hi> will allow in the number of <hi>Saints,</hi> and that they might truely call God <hi>Father;</hi> and yet one of them ſays in his Prayer to God; <hi>I have gone aſtray like a loſt Sheep, O ſeek thy Servant,</hi> Pſ. 119.176. the other ſays; <hi>Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners, of whom I am chief,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. and if after their Examples,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102911:33"/>and that of the <hi>penitent Publican</hi> we come to Church, and <hi>confeſs</hi> our Sins, and deſire <hi>God to be Merciful to us Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> and alſo after the Example of the <hi>poor Prodigal,</hi> we ariſe and go to our Father, and ſay unto him, <hi>Father we have ſinned againſt Heaven and before thee, and are not worthy to be called thy Children;</hi> we may hope to go back again to our Houſes <hi>juſtified before the envious Elder Brother, and proud Phariſee, that Cenſure and condemn us for our Humility and Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>AS nothing is more uſual than for <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pogate their falſe and pernicious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines by <hi>Fire and Sword,</hi> and all the ſtudied Arts of <hi>Cruelty and Violence,</hi> that what is wanting of <hi>Truth</hi> on their ſide, may be made up with <hi>blind furious Zeal, and ungovernable Rage,</hi> ſo none are more forward to ſhift the <hi>Odium</hi> of ſuch bloody Proceedings, and caſt it
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102911:34"/>upon others that are not guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to make loud Outcries of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> which in reality muſt be charged upon themſelves, and laid at their own <hi>Doors.</hi> Thus of old the <hi>Arians</hi> dealt with the <hi>Orthodox Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> complain'd of hard Uſage from them, and of their great Sufferings for Conſcience ſake, and yet none were more bloody Perſecutors than themſelves, as the <hi>Orthodox</hi> found by ſad Experience, when theſe Men had gotten <hi>the Power</hi> into their own Hands, from whom they ſuffered more than ever they did from the <hi>most barbarous Nations,</hi> or under the worſt <hi>Heathen Perſecutions.</hi> And thus their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have carried themſelves towards the <hi>Churches of Chriſt,</hi> where they have had means and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to ſhew the Savageneſs of their Natures and Diſpoſitions, witneſs the <hi>diſmal Tragedies</hi> they acted at their <hi>firſt riſe</hi> in <hi>Manſter,</hi> and other Parts of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> which were ſo <hi>barbarous and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> that the <hi>Modern Anabaptiſts</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>to be aſham'd of them,</hi> and of the <hi>levelling carnal Principles,</hi> which their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102911:34"/>
                  <hi>firſt Founders held:</hi> However this by the way ſhews their <hi>Religion to be very bad, whoſe Foundation was laid in Rebellion and Blood,</hi> and ſo indeed has it been propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated ever ſince, when any fair occaſion has been offered for the diſcovery of their Intentions; witneſs their <hi>Perſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King</hi> Charles <hi>the Martyr,</hi> and ſome of his loyal Subjects, to the very <hi>Gates of Death,</hi> and ſome of them to <hi>ſtrange Cities,</hi> in which theſe Men had a great Hand, being ſome <hi>of the worſt, tho' moſt potent in</hi> Cromwel's <hi>Army, who with their aſſiſtance rul'd all, and accompliſh'd thoſe Villianies, which are a Scandal to our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Reproach to the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet Page 45, ſpeaking to a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our Church, <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſays, <hi>art not thou a deſperate Perſecutor of the Children of God? He is their Father whom thou Perſecuteſt;</hi> Strange confidence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed! that this Man ſhould not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to complain of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> who was himſelf a great <hi>Perſecutor,</hi> as this very Book of his ſhews; wherein he treats us with bitter Words and railing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102911:35"/>Language, which is one kind of <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and not the leaſt neither, even that of the <hi>Tongue;</hi> for what <hi>Moſes</hi> calls <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maels mocking,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtyles his <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.9. compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. and I doubt the <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of the <hi>Hand</hi> would ſoon follow, if it lay in theſe Mens Power this way to hurt us; and perhaps they might think it meritorious, and that they ſhould do God good Service in deſtroying us, as the mad <hi>Jews</hi> did when they <hi>killed Chriſt's Diſciples,</hi> Joh. 16.2. This is certain, that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and other <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who now cry out ſo much of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> have proved themſelves <hi>deſperate Perſecutors,</hi> as often as they have <hi>had Opportunities to ſhew it,</hi> witneſs their <hi>Ejecting, Decimating and Sequeſtrating, their Impriſoning, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, and Beheading ſo many of the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al party in</hi> Cromwell<hi>'s Days, who by theſe Mens advice and aſſiſtance, acted all thoſe Villanies upon his faithful fellow Subjects, and imbrued his Hands in his gracious Sovereign's innocent Blood, in the ſhedding whereof all the Sectaries concurred, but eſpecially the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102911:35"/>Anabaptiſts, who ſome of them ſat as his Judges, and condemned him; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <note n="*">See the Life of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt p. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>interrupted him in his laſt Devotions, and offer'd Affronts to him in his dying Moments and Agonies, not ſuffering him to Pray or Dye in quiet, without diſturbing his Charitable Soul with unuſual rudeneſs and injuries,</hi> witneſs their <hi>Rebellion</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe againſt <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Second,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conduct of the <hi>Duke of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> a conſiderable part of whoſe <hi>Commanders, Officers</hi> and <hi>Soldiers</hi> were <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and this <hi>reſiſtance</hi> of their <hi>rightful Sovereigns</hi> tho' contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and the <hi>practice</hi> of all the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians;</hi> yet theſe Men <hi>Juſtify, Defend</hi> and <hi>Canonize ſuch for Saints and Martyrs as died in it, and were executed for it,</hi> as may be ſeen in a Rhiming Pamphlet of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin Keach's</hi> entituled<note n="*">See diſtreſſed <hi>Sion</hi> relieved. p. 25, 26, 27. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where ſome that were Rebels to two if not 3 Kings are named as Saints and Martyrs.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſtreſſed</hi> Sion <hi>releived or the Garment of Praiſe for the Spirit of Heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> wherein are to be found diverſe inſtances of ſuch <hi>Army Saints</hi> and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102911:36"/>
                  <hi>Fighting Martyrs,</hi> tho' I dare ſay, the <hi>firſt</hi> the Chriſtian Church ever heard of ſince the Foundation of it, <hi>all the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in Queen</hi> Mary's <hi>Days, and under the Ten Perſecutions, being Strangers to Carnal Weapons, and accuſtomed only to Spiritual ones, even Prayers and Tears, thinking the other unlawful to be uſed againſt their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, or for Chriſt's ſake, whoſe Kingdom is not of this World, nor are his Servants to fight for him, as himſelf expreſly affirms,</hi> Joh. 18.36. <hi>So contrary to the Goſpel</hi> and the holy <hi>Chriſtian Martyrs</hi> is theſe <hi>pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Proteſtants Practice,</hi> and ſo is that paſſage in the <hi>ſolemn League and Covenant, the Presbyterian Idol, to which they would have all Hands lifted up, and all Knees to bow, we ſhall in like manner, without reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of Perſons, endeavour the extirpation of Popery and Prelacy, (that is Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellours and Commiſſaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Arch Deacons and all other Eccleſiaſtical Officers depending on that Hierarchy) we ſhall alſo with all Faithfulneſs endeavour the diſcovery of all ſuch as have been or ſhall be Malignants,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by hindring
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102911:36"/>the Reformation of Religion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Parties,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>amongst the People contrary to this League and Covenant, that they be brought to publick Tryal, and receive condign Puniſhment, as the degree of their Offence ſhall require or deſerve;</hi> by which Clauſes they are bound to <hi>deſtroy our Church Root and Branch, and all others too that ſhall help us,</hi> or hinder them in this <hi>reforming Work,</hi> which any one would think could not be done without a <hi>bloody Perſecution,</hi> unleſs therefore <hi>John Bunyan</hi> and his Party <hi>renounce the ſolemn League and Covenant, and their other Perſecuting Oaths and Books,</hi> and alſo all their <hi>violent and cruel Practiſes, in this and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> let them not for <hi>ſhame complain of Perſecution,</hi> who have been, and are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>great Accuſers and grand Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of their Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>OUR Author (I ſuppoſe) being ſenſible of the ſmall ſucceſs his railing againſt the Common Prayer may
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102911:37"/>have to withdraw any rational Perſons love from it, or to raiſe his hatred there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, bethinks himſelf of better and ſtronger Arguments againſt it, and endeavours to perſwade the World, that the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are on his ſide, and do in ſeveral places manifeſtly condemn it, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed would effectually do his Buſineſs, if he could but prove this vainglorious Aſſertion; but how well that is done, we come next to examine, for p. 35, 36. <hi>Jo. Bunyan,</hi> ſays, <hi>The Common Prayer Book is a meer humane Invention and Inſtitution, which God is ſo far from owning of, that he expreſly forbids it, with any other ſuch like, and that by manifold Sayings in his moſt holy and bleſſed Word;</hi> and one of the Texts he quotes is <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.9. <hi>It is better to dwell in the corner of the Houſe top than with a brawling Woman in a wide Houſe,</hi> which perhaps is a <hi>miſtake of the Printer,</hi> being nothing at all to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but all the other <hi>Texts</hi> he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being altogether as <hi>Impertinent, and this a ſecond Edition</hi> of the Diſcourſe, I am tempted to think this is no errour of the Preſs, but what the Ignorant Author
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102911:37"/>might imagine a good Proof of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs of Forms of Prayer, and as good Proof indeed it is, as thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which he there inſerts, as <hi>Mark</hi> 7.7, 8. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Doctrines the Commandments of Men, for laying aſide the Commandment of God, ye hold the Tradition of Men, as the waſhing of Pots and Cups, and many other ſuch like things ye do,</hi> where 'tis plain our Saviour condemn'd the <hi>Hypocritical Scribes and Pharaſees</hi> for <hi>preferring</hi> their <hi>vain Tradations</hi> (of which they had a great many, and particularly the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> mentioned <hi>ver.</hi> 11.) <hi>before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God,</hi> i. e. they forbad Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to help their Parents when they were in want, if they had either raſhly made a Vow never to do it, or had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted their Subſtance to pious uſes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Fifth Commandment,</hi> which requires Children to relieve their Parents when they need it; that being one way of honouring them; and thus thoſe Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical Scribes and Pharaſees were very curious in cleanſing their Pots and Cups, leſt themſelves ſhould be pollut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102911:38"/>with any Legal uncleanneſs; but yet they notoriouſly neglected thoſe great <hi>Moral Duties</hi> which were <hi>plainly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> and alſo <hi>ſignified by them,</hi> even <hi>the cleanſing their Hearts and Lives from the filthineſs of Sin;</hi> as is evident from <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23. and <hi>Luke</hi> 11.39. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto him; Now do ye Phariſees make clean the outſide of the Cup and Platter, but your inward part is full of Ravening and Wickedneſs:</hi> But how does the <hi>Jewiſh Corban,</hi> and their <hi>ſuperſtitious Waſhing of Pots and Cups, conclude againſt the uſe of the</hi> Common Prayer Book? Do we <hi>equal</hi> or <hi>prefer it to the Bible,</hi> as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did <hi>theſe things</hi> to the <hi>Commandments of God?</hi> And what <hi>Commandment</hi> do we break in the uſe of the <hi>Common Prayer Book,</hi> as they did the <hi>Fifth</hi> in the Practice of their <hi>Corban?</hi> Certainly if this place has any reſpect to Prayer, <hi>it more forceably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes againſt their extemporary Prayers,</hi> which they conſtantly uſe in their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, whilſt in the mean time, <hi>they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that excellent Form which Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has Commanded,</hi> Luke 11.2. <hi>When
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102911:38"/>ye Pray, ſay Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. So that with more reaſon any one may think they themſelves are the <hi>modern Scribes and Phariſees, that are here Condemned by our Saviour,</hi> of whom he ſays, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Full well ye reject the Commandment of God, even that concerning the</hi> Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>that you may keep your own Tradition, even that of</hi> extemporary Prayer, <hi>which is a meer Invention of Men, and no where commanded in the Holy Scriptures:</hi> But in our Common Prayer Book, we retain that <hi>Divine Prayer;</hi> and all our other Prayers are Compoſed according to it; 'tis after that manner we Pray in all the reſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9. ſo that in the <hi>uſe of the Common Prayer,</hi> we keep the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of Chriſt,</hi> and they in <hi>deſpiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof reject it;</hi> and then, <hi>theſe Words which they urge againſt us, turn upon themſelves;</hi> and ſo does that of <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.30, 31, 32. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelf, that thou be not ſnared by following them, after that they be deſtroyed from before thee, and that thou enquire not after their Gods, ſaying, how did thoſe Nations ſerve their Gods? Even ſo will I do likewiſe; thou
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102911:39"/>ſhalt not do ſo unto the Lord thy God; for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry abomination unto the Lord, which he hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, have they done unto their Gods, for even their Sons and their Daughters have they burnt in the Fire unto their Gods; what thing ſoever I command you, obſerve to do it, thou ſhalt not add thereto, nor diminiſh from it.</hi> For, <hi>firſt,</hi> are <hi>we</hi> ſuch <hi>heathen People</hi> as theſe <hi>ſeven Nations were?</hi> Do <hi>we Worſhip the Hoſt of Heaven,</hi> Sun Moon and Stars as <hi>they</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Do <hi>we Sacrifice our Children to Idols as they did?</hi> If this were true, they might have ſome pretence for urging theſe Texts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and from them alſo might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that they are bound to cut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Branch, (as by the Covenant they are S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to do)</hi> even as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were oblig'd to deſtroy the <hi>ſeven Idolatrous Nations.</hi> But, <hi>if none of theſe things can be laid to our Charge, who Worſhip the God of Heaven, and his Son Jeſus Christ, and abhor Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, with what Face dare they produce ſuch Scriptures against us, as concern none but Idolaters?</hi> In the next place, <hi>How do we add to the Word of God, or diminiſh from it,</hi> by the uſe of the Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Book? Do we thereby, make <hi>more
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102911:39"/>or leſs Canonical Books</hi> of Holy Scripture than the Church of God has allow'd and approv'd of in all Ages? Do we not acknowledge and believe every <hi>tittle</hi> of the Holy Scriptures, <hi>and abominate the leaſt addition or diminution to them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome call it <hi>Divine Service,</hi> and the <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> is Bound up with the <hi>Bible,</hi> and is not this an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Word of God? No, by no means; for when we call the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Divine Service,</hi> we give it that Title from the <hi>Object thereof,</hi> which is <hi>Almighty God,</hi> to whom all our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are directed and offered up; and we are not ſo Preſumptuous, as to intend thereby, that they are of equal Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the Holy Scriptures, or that God himſelf, is the immediate Author of them, (excepting that only of <hi>Our Father</hi>) but only that Prayer being the Service of God, and our Churches Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Compoſed according to the Rule of his Word, ſome on that account call it <hi>Divine Service,</hi> tho' that Title be not to be found in the Book it ſelf, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can be no Objection againſt it;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102911:40"/>and as for the Binding it up with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that does not make it any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, no more than the <hi>Contents</hi> of the <hi>ſeveral Chapters,</hi> and the <hi>Marginal Notes</hi> can be ſaid to be part of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which yet are Bound up with them; but to ſhew the great value we have for the Word of God, it is order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Common Prayer Book, that in this ſolemn Worſhip of Almighty God, <hi>ſome Pſalms and Chapters out of the Old and New Teſtament, ſhall be read every Morning and every Evening;</hi> wherein, we follow the Example of <hi>Christ</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the <hi>former of which, did read part of the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah <hi>to the People, and it was his Cuſtom to do ſo,</hi> Luk. 4.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. and the latter after <hi>the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law and the Prophets preached to the Congregation,</hi> Act. 13.15, 16, 17. <hi>&amp;c. a thing which is never Practiced (as I am credibly inform'd) by</hi> John Bunyan <hi>and his Party, no more than it is by the Quakers, which ſhews the little regard they both have to the Holy Scripture, and that they prefer their own Extemporary Prayers and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments before it,</hi> with <hi>what Forehead</hi> then
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102911:40"/>can this <hi>Author</hi> pretend that we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value the Word of God, either by add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>to it, or diminiſhing from it?</hi> which not <hi>we</hi> but <hi>they themſelves</hi> are <hi>guilty of;</hi> for they never <hi>read the holy Scriptures</hi> to their <hi>Congregations as we do;</hi> but inſtead thereof pretend that their <hi>Extemporary Prayers and rambling Diſcourſes are the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate dictates of the Holy Ghoſt; and then both muſt be as good Scripture as any in the Bible, which is truly to add to the Word of God, and to break the foregoing Precept of</hi> Moſes, and that other to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. <hi>Ye ſhall not add unto the Word which I command you, neither ſhall you diminiſh ought from it, that ye may keep the Commandments of your Lord your God, which I command you;</hi> which theſe Men thus openly neglect and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn, in rejecting that <hi>Form of Prayer</hi> which Chriſt requires all his Diſciples to uſe; and ſo thoſe <hi>two other Texts</hi> he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.6. concern <hi>themſelves and not us,</hi> in that <hi>pretending to pray in the very Words of the Spirit, they thereby add unto the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of St.</hi> John <hi>new ones of their own,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:102911:41"/>and therefore have all the reaſon in the World to fear <hi>the Plagues there threatned, and leſt God ſhould reprove them, and they ſhould be found Liars;</hi> laſtly, as for <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. to verſe 24. how does that effect the <hi>Common Prayer Book?</hi> Do we therein teach the <hi>Obſervation of new Moons and Sabbaths, and the Worſhiping of Angels?</hi> Or do we therein forbid to <hi>touch, taſte or handle thoſe things which God has allow'd,</hi> (as ſome of the <hi>ancient Hereticks</hi> did? as particularly <hi>Marriage, and unclean Meats, which they held to be unlawful) but if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of all this can be faſtned upon us, what Impudence is it for this Man to produce this place of St.</hi> Paul <hi>againſt us?</hi> eſpecially when we may with better reaſon urge it againſt him and his Adherents; for do not they <hi>forbid to touch,</hi> i. e. <hi>any Form of Prayer, even that which our Lord Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Do not they forbid to taſte,</hi> i. e. <hi>any Meat that has blood in it, which they hold unlawful to be eaten?</hi> do not they <hi>forbid</hi> to <hi>handle,</hi> i. e. <hi>Pſalms, Hymns and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Songs, which St.</hi> Paul <hi>has commanded to be Sung?</hi> And what is all this but to ſubject others to their <hi>own Ordinances,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102911:41"/>which are but the Commandments and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men?</hi> Thus thoſe <hi>very Texts of Scripture, which theſe Men fooliſhly bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> againſt us, ſometimes <hi>urging them againſt Infant Baptiſm, ſometimes againſt Sprinkling, ſometimes againſt the Croſs, and other Ceremonies, and ſometimes againſt our Common Prayer,</hi> (as our Author here) <hi>do all turn upon themſelves, and give them a deadly and incurable Wound.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>BUT if none of the aforementioned Texts will ſerve the turn, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prove miſcheivous to him, <hi>Jo. Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yan</hi> has <hi>Two in reſerve</hi> that ſhall effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally confute us; the firſt is <hi>Zachar.</hi> 12.10. <hi>I will pour upon the Houſe of</hi> David <hi>and Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>the Spirit of Grace and Supplication,</hi> &amp;c. which being Propheſied of the Goſpel Days, he thence infers that the Spirit is the Author of all our Prayers, and therefore muſt needs invent and dictate them to us; in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to which, I ſay,</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:102911:42"/>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1st.</hi> That what we Tranſlate the <hi>Spirit of Supplication,</hi> may as properly be rendred the <hi>Spirit of Mercy,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Seventy</hi> render it, the <hi>Word</hi> in the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal</hi> ſignifying as well to <hi>ſhew Mercy as to Pray;</hi> and then the Argument de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from this Place, is of no force at all; that becauſe God wou'd have Mercy upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> (who are here meant by the <hi>Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of</hi> Jeruſalem) in bringing them out of Captivity, that therefore we Chriſtians, have a Promiſe here to Pray by the Spirit, in that Senſe our Author wou'd have it.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> If we allow the <hi>Vulgar Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation,</hi> in rendring it the <hi>Spirit of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,</hi> and that this Prophecy has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>Goſpel Days,</hi> it was <hi>fulfilled on the Day of Pentecost,</hi> when ſo many Thouſands were Converted by St <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Sermon, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>they were first pricked to the Heart,</hi> Acts 2.37. <hi>i. e.</hi> for all their Sins, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly for that <hi>great one, of Crucifying of Jeſus Christ,</hi> and ſo, <hi>they looked on him whom they had pierced,</hi> (as the Prophet
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:102911:42"/>foretold they ſhould, in the ſame place) by the <hi>Eye of Faith and Repentance,</hi> and received from him, <hi>the Spirit of Grace and Supplication,</hi> i. e. ſuch miraculous Gifts and Graces, as were beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apoſtles and firſt Diſciples of our Lord, and were confined to that Age; when was fulfilled alſo that Prophecy of <hi>Joel,</hi> Chap. 2.28, 29. as St. <hi>Peter</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.16. <hi>This is it</hi> (i. e. thoſe miraculous Gifts which you ſee us have) <hi>which was ſpoken by the Prophet</hi> Joel.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt is called, the <hi>Spirit of Supplication,</hi> becauſe all thoſe Prayers in the Old and New Teſtament; which were made by the Prophets and Apoſtles, and <hi>particularly that of our Lord, were immediately Inſpired and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctated by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and they are left upon Record, as ſo many <hi>Patterns</hi> for us to Compoſe our Prayers by them on the like occaſions; and ſo <hi>the Spirit helps our Infirmities, in teaching us to Pray according to theſe Scripture Forms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> Becauſe, <hi>the Holy Spirit ſtirs us up to this Duty, and aſſiſts us with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102911:43"/>Deſires in the actual Performance of it;</hi> on this account alſo he may be Styled <hi>The Spirit of Supplication,</hi> altho' he does not Dictate to us the very words of our Prayer, (as he did to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles) <hi>and for any to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend he does, unleſs they can produce the like Miracles as the Prophets and Apoſtles wrought, is the greateſt vanity and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5thly.</hi> We may on as good, or better Grounds affirm, that he is called the Spirit of Supplication, becauſe, <hi>He aſſiſts us in the Compoſure and Devout uſe of godly Forms of Prayer,</hi> ſince 'tis ſaid, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.11. <hi>In that Day ſhall there be a great Mourning in Jeruſalem, as the Mourning of Hadadrimmon in the Valley of Megiddo;</hi> and how that was, we are given to underſtand, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25. <hi>And</hi> Jeremiah <hi>lamented for</hi> Joſiah, <hi>and all the Singing-Men and Singing-Women ſpake of</hi> Joſiah <hi>in their Lamentations to this Day, and made them an Ordinance in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> had a <hi>Form of Prayer and Lamentations,</hi> to be Sung with <hi>doleful Notes every Year</hi> to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102911:43"/>the great Loſs of that <hi>good King</hi> Joſiah: And <hi>if the Spirit of Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will cauſe us to Mourn in our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers before the Lord as the</hi> Jews <hi>did, we muſt compoſe and uſe the like Form as they did; and ſuch a Form have we in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book, wherein, on</hi> January <hi>the Thirtieth, we Mourn for our</hi> Engliſh Joſiah, <hi>I mean, King</hi> Charles <hi>the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr; and therefore it ought to be continued as an Ordinance among us, like that of</hi> Jeremiah<hi>'s among the</hi> Iſraelites; <hi>and 'tis to the Shame and Scandal of ſome of our Clergy, that this Day is antiquated, and the Anniverſary-Service diſuſed in ſeveral Places, and I mention it for no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but in hopes they may be ſpeedily Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, or exemplarily Puniſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s ſecond reſerved Proof, is, p. 112. <hi>How will the Favourers of ſuch a Practice,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Forms of Prayer) an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that Scripture, which commandeth the Church ſhould turn away from ſuch as have a Form of Godlineſs, but deny the Power thereof?</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. and this he had urged before, p. 57. <hi>The great Cheat that the Devil and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102911:44"/>deludes the World withal, is to make them continue in the Form of any Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Form of Preaching, of Hearing, of Praying,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Theſe are they that have a Form of Godlineſs, but deny the Power, from ſuch turn away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Text alſo, tho' he repeats it, and puts falſe gloſſes upon it, makes nothing to his purpoſe, but rather againſt him; for, 1st. St. <hi>Paul</hi> does not here <hi>Condemn a Form of Godlineſs,</hi> having Commanded it a little before, in the very ſame Epiſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Hold fast the Form of ſound Words, which thou hast heard of me:</hi> And ſurely the ſame Apoſtle who Commands us to <hi>hold faſt,</hi> cannot be ſuppoſed ſo changeable, as to Command us to <hi>turn away</hi> from <hi>a Form of Godlineſs;</hi> that <hi>can never be the meaning of the Place, to make the ſame inſpired Penman, to Write Contradictions in the ſame Epiſtle:</hi> When therefore he upbraids them, with having <hi>a Form of Godlineſs,</hi> it was only becauſe it was ſeparated from the <hi>Power thereof;</hi> i. e. they had put aſunder thoſe things which God would have united; as Almighty
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102911:44"/>God upbraids the <hi>Jews</hi> with the <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their Sacrifices, their vain Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Incenſe, new Moons and Sabbaths,</hi> as if he did not <hi>require, but abominate them;</hi> and yet theſe things God himſelf had ſtrictly enjoyn'd under great Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11, 12, 13. But the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he is there ſaid to <hi>loath them,</hi> is, becauſe their <hi>Hands were full of Blood,</hi> they did not bring theſe Sacrifices and Oblations, with ſuch <hi>pure Hearts,</hi> and <hi>clean Hands,</hi> with which he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to be Offer'd at his Altar, <hi>ver.</hi> 15, 16, 17. Now this Author might with as much or more reaſon from theſe Texts infer, that God had forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People to Offer any Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or Incenſe, to keep any new Moons or Sabbaths; as from the other Text to pretend that God forbids a <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> whereas indeed nothing but the <hi>Abuſe</hi> of theſe Religious Duties is reprehended in either place; and when St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3.5. (for this is ſpoken to him, to whom this Epiſtle was ſent) to <hi>turn away from ſuch,</hi> the Apoſtle gives him Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:102911:45"/>
                  <hi>what to do</hi> with ſuch notorious Hypocrites, as <hi>had the Form of Godlineſs, but denyed the Power thereof;</hi> even <hi>to caſt them out of all Chriſtian Society, by the Cenſures of the Church, and ſo to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from them, but not from the Form of Godlineſs, which was good ſtill, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the worſe for theſe Mens abuſe of it: Turn away from ſuch Men, but not from ſuch a Form:</hi> So that this Text like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (as all the reſt he hath hitherto urged, if it has any reſpect to a <hi>Form of Prayer,</hi> as this Objector inſinuates) is a good Argument for the <hi>Lawfulneſs of ſuch a Form,</hi> and will juſtifie us in the uſe thereof, provided we let the <hi>Power of Godlineſs</hi> go along with it, and on this account St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> or the Church, (as this Man would have it) to <hi>hold faſt that Form of ſound Words, which he had heard of him;</hi> and in another place to the ſame purpoſe with this and the former, he ſays, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5. <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to wholeſome Words, even the Words of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and to the Doctrine which is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102911:45"/>according to Godlineſs, he is Proud, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, but doting about Queſtions, and ſtrifes of Words; whereof cometh En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Strife, Railings, evil Surmiſings, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Diſputings of Men of corrupt Minds, and deſtitute of the Truth, ſuppoſing that Gain is Godlineſs, from ſuch withdraw thy ſelf;</hi> i. e. <hi>by paſſing the Sentence of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication upon them:</hi> Now do not <hi>all three places concern</hi> Jo. Bunyan <hi>and his Party, who teach otherwiſe, and who condemn that Form of ſound Words, which Chriſt himſelf has taught us, and St.</hi> Paul <hi>commands us to hold faſt? Are they not alſo Proud, falſe Accuſers, Trayterous, Heady, High-minded, and plainly decipher'd under the black Character the Apoſtle there gives of ſuch as reject that Form of ſound Words, which is according to Godlineſs?</hi> And ſo we have hence alſo gain'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother good Proof of the <hi>Lawfulneſs of the Common Prayer Book,</hi> as being a <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> and containing a <hi>Form of ſound and wholeſome Words;</hi> and if we joyn the <hi>Power thereof</hi> with it, we may and ought to continue in the Devout uſe thereof, and never to Teach or
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102911:46"/>Practiſe otherwiſe, for fear of falling under the <hi>black Character</hi> before given, and more at large ſet down in that Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>BUT our Author having had ſuch bad Succeſs in the choice of his Arguments againſt Forms of Prayer, which prove no <hi>ſuch thing,</hi> but rather the <hi>Lawfulneſs of them,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> of their <hi>withdrawing from them for the ſake of their extemporary Effuſions;</hi> let us, in the next place, ſee what <hi>better Arguments</hi> he advances to make good his Pretences <hi>to Pray by the Spirit,</hi> and that ſuch <hi>extemporary Prayers are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Scriptures:</hi> As for his Text out of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14, 15, which is the chief Proof he brings, it is no Proof for but againſt him, as I have already ſhewn in my firſt Chapter, and ſhall now far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make appear.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:102911:46"/>
               <p>For, 1ſt. This is no <hi>Command</hi> but an <hi>Example,</hi> and that of an <hi>extraordinary and miraculous Nature,</hi> even by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Adverſary, St. <hi>Paul's Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Spirit</hi> being <hi>accompanyed</hi> with the <hi>Gift of Tongues,</hi> and therefore he ſays, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>I thank God, I ſpeak with Tongues more than you all;</hi> ſo that unleſs <hi>Jo, Bunyan and his Party had the ſame miraculous Gift of Tongues, (which I preſume they have not the Confidence to pretend to) they cannot urge St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Example for their pretences to Pray by the Spirit, having it not in the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Meaſure which he had:</hi> They may as well <hi>pretend to Viſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations</hi> which were vouchſafed to that <hi>great Apoſtle</hi> in an high degree, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>caught up into the third Heaven, and hearing there ſuch Words as are not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> i. e. <hi>not poſſible for a Man to utter,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.2, 3, 4. They may as well ſay, <hi>I have been caught up into Paradice, as I will Pray with the Spirit in the ſame manner that St.</hi> Paul <hi>did:</hi> But if theſe Words ſhould (as I think they cannot) refer to the <hi>ordinary Gifts of the Spirit,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:102911:47"/>then we may from them deduce, not only the <hi>Lawfulneſs, but neceſſity</hi> alſo, of uſing a <hi>Form of Prayer,</hi> (as I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerv'd) being ſo cloſely connected with the latter part of the firſt, <hi>I will Sing with the Spirit, and I will Sing with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo:</hi> Now ſince all Chriſtians make uſe of <hi>Forms in Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or elſe the <hi>Congregation can never joyn with them;</hi> and <hi>when they do, they may Sing with the Spirit:</hi> What Reaſon can there be given, why they may not as well <hi>Pray by the Spirit,</hi> altho' they Pray according to <hi>ſet Forms</hi> which are before them? So that this is as <hi>unlucky a Text for his purpoſe, as the Author could poſſibly have lighted upon;</hi> for inſtead of concluding againſt Forms of Prayer, it is ſuch a convincing Argument of the <hi>Lawfulneſs of them, as I believe neither be nor all his Party will ever be able to Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His next Argument, is from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Likewiſe the Spirit alſo helpeth our Infirmities, for we know not what we ſhould Pray for as we ought, but the Spirt it ſelf maketh Interceſſion for us, with Groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102911:47"/>that cannot be uttered;</hi> which he ſets down in the Title-Page, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats and flouriſhes with ſeveral times in his Book, and does thus Paraphraſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, p. 29. <hi>Conſider firſt, the Perſon ſpeaking, even</hi> Paul, <hi>and in his Perſon all the Apoſtles; We Apoſtles, we extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Officers, the wiſe Maſter Builders, that have ſome of us been caught up into Paradice; we know not what we ſhould Pray for:</hi> And p. 31. <hi>The Apoſtles when they were at beſt, yea when the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt aſſiſted them, yet then were they fain to come off with Sighs and Groans, fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhort of expreſſing their Mind, but with Sighs and Groans which cannot be uttered.</hi> A falſe and ſilly Paraphraſe indeed; for <hi>first,</hi> When St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays [We] or [I] we are not to underſtand it always as ſpoken of himſelf; but he takes upon him the Perſon of others, and ſometimes ſuch as are <hi>unregenerate,</hi> even after his <hi>own Converſion,</hi> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8, 9.14.23.25. where he ſays, <hi>Sin wrought in me all manner of Concupiſcence; Sin reviv'd and I dyed: I am carnal ſold, under Sin; I ſee another Law in my Members, warring
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102911:48"/>againſt the Law of my Mind, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me into Captivity to the Law of Sin and Death; with my Fleſh I ſerve the Law of Sin:</hi> All which Expreſſions by no means agree to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was Converted before this, being quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Nature of a <hi>Regenerate Man,</hi> who is ſaid in other places of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to be <hi>free from Sin, and the Servant of Righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 6.18. <hi>That the Law of the Spirit of Life in Christ, has made me free from the Law of Sin and Death,</hi> Rom. 8.2. <hi>That he has crucified the Fleſh, with the Affections and Luſts,</hi> Gal. 5.24. <hi>That Sin does not Reign in his mortal Body, that he ſhould obey it in the Lusts thereof,</hi> Rom. 6.12. So that unleſs we can <hi>twiſt Contradictions, we cannot ſuppoſe St.</hi> Paul <hi>to ſpeak of himſelf, in that ſeventh Chapter, but only of a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſing Chriſtian, or a Convinced but not Converted Perſon,</hi> and nothing is more uſual, than for Prophets and Apoſtles, to ſpeak in the Perſon of others, when they ſay [I] or [We] did <hi>ſo</hi> or <hi>ſo;</hi> for we cannot ſuppoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, or indeed any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102911:48"/>Chriſtian ſo very Ignorant, as not to know <hi>to whom,</hi> and <hi>thro' whom,</hi> and <hi>for what to Pray;</hi> and therefore the, <hi>we know not</hi> &amp;c. muſt have reſpect to other Men, and ſuch as were Heathens and Unconverted, who had not before heard of Chriſt, or ſeen the Goſpel, where there are Rules laid down, and thoſe Dictated and written by the Holy Spirit, how they and all Men ought to Pray, even <hi>to our Father which is in Heaven, thro' his beloved Son Jeſus Chriſt, for ſuch Lawful things as are according to his Will:</hi> And when Men Pray thus, according to that excellent Form which Chriſt has preſcribed, his Holy Spirit will alſo aſſiſt them with <hi>good Deſires,</hi> ſo that they ſhall Heartily wiſh and long for thoſe things for which they Pray, with ſubmiſſion to the Will of God; <hi>and thus the Spirit helpeth our Infirmities, in revealing to us the Holy Scriptures, where thoſe that were Ignorant before, are taught how to Pray as they ought.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our Author goes on with his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe, p. 30.31. <hi>The Apoſtles when they were at best, yea when they were aſſiſted
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102911:49"/>with the Holy Ghost, yet then they were fain to come off with Sighs and Groans,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mark here,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>they could not ſo well and fully come off, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of performing this Duty, as theſe in our Days think they can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But is not this another good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Forms of Prayer, when the Apoſtles themſelves ſtood in need of them, and therefore deſired <hi>Chriſt to teach them ſuch a Form as</hi> John <hi>had taught his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> Luke, 11.1. <hi>Lord teach us to Pray as</hi> John <hi>alſo taught his Diſciples:</hi> And certainly they had need to be taught ſuch a <hi>Form to help them out,</hi> if they were ſuch <hi>Bunglers at Prayer</hi> as <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> repreſents them, <hi>viz.</hi> That they were not able to make an end of the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they had begun in the Congregation, but were forc'd to break off abruptly, perhaps in the midſt thereof; which muſt needs cauſe Shame to themſelves, and Diſappointment and Confuſion to the whole Aſſembly, which all their <hi>Sighs and Groans,</hi> would never be able to compenſate; but no Man of Senſe, can believe, the Apoſtles ever Prayed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102911:49"/>at this rate in the Church of God, where they command all things to be done <hi>Decently and in order, and to the Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.26.40. For, what <hi>Order, Decency, or Edifying</hi> is there in <hi>Sighs and Groans,</hi> which Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites may utter, as well as Sincere Chriſtians? And when either does it, who can tell the meaning of them? And may not a Man <hi>edifie as much by the</hi> Quakers <hi>Silent-meetings, as by ſuch Sighs and Groans, which have no certain and determinate Signification as Words and Speeches have?</hi> And yet if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Jo. Bunyan,</hi> theſe were a good part of the Apoſtles Prayers, even in their publik Aſſemblies; but the Proof which he brings for it, <hi>is Simple and Ridiculous,</hi> viz. <hi>[For the Spirit it ſelf, maketh Interceſſion for us, with Groanings which cannot be uttered]</hi> Whereas theſe are not the <hi>Groanings of the Apoſtles,</hi> or of <hi>any Man elſe upon the Face of the Earth,</hi> but <hi>the Groanings of the Holy-Ghost himſelf in Heaven,</hi> where toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>with the Lord Jeſus, he maketh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us, at the Right-hand of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102911:50"/>God, and that in a very fervent and powerful manner, which St.</hi> Paul <hi>calls his Groanings which cannot be uttered, and therefore can never be applyed to the Groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Men, which are always heard, and make a ſound in their very utterance:</hi> So fooliſh and preſumptuous is this Man in Expounding and Applying this Text; eſpecially in endeavouring to prove from it, that the Holy Spirit does invent and dictate to us, the very words of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; for here are no <hi>Words</hi> at all proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Spirit, but only <hi>Groanings;</hi> How then <hi>can this place prove, that the Spirit ſuggeſts to us the Words of our Prayer, when he interceeds for us without Words, even with Groanings,</hi> (but pray miſtake not) <hi>not with ſuch Groanings as</hi> Jo. Bunyan <hi>and his Party makes, and may be heard in every corner of the Houſe, and in the very Streets, but with Groanings that cannot be uttered:</hi> And that theſe are the inexpreſſible Deſires of Chriſt and the Spirit of God in Heaven, is plain from <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27. <hi>He that ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Hearts,</hi> (i. e. <hi>Almighty God, whoſe Prerogative it is</hi>) <hi>knoweth what is the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102911:50"/>Mind of the Spirit, becauſe he maketh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for the Saints according to the Will of God.</hi> So that this Text alſo, as all the reſt, turns upon the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector, and proves, that the <hi>Spirit does not put Words into their Mouths,</hi> nor cauſe thoſe <hi>Groanings,</hi> which are <hi>ſo loud and frequent in their Meetings;</hi> the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits <hi>Groanings here, being ſaid to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noiſe or ſound, without utterance or expreſſion; they are ſuch as cannot be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered:</hi> Whence I may well conclude, <hi>that</hi> Jo. Bunyan<hi>'s extemporary Prayers, his diſmal Groans, and thoſe Fits and Agonies of the Spirit, which (he ſays) he was ſometimes in, when he was ſtrongly perſwaded to leave off, and to ſeek the Lord no longer,</hi> p. 71. I may conclude, (I ſay) that <hi>this is a great Cheat of the Devil and Antichrist, by which he does delude and deceive the World, by which Men would perſwade themſelves and others, that they Pray with the Spirit, that they Preach with the Spirit, and Hear with the Spirit, even with the ſame extraordinary Spirit which St.</hi> Paul <hi>had, when there is no ſuch thing, but they are rather poſſeſſed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102911:51"/>by an evil Spirit, which makes them think and ſpeak ſo highly and vain-gloriouſly of themſelves, and ſo contemptibly and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably of others; their Mouth ſpeaketh great ſwelling Words, having Mens Perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage: Theſe be they that ſeparate themſelves, Senſual, having not the Spirit,</hi> Jud. ver. 16.19.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAving ſaid in the Concluſion of the former Chapter, that</hi> J. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyan <hi>and his Party,</hi> have not the Spirit <hi>to which they ſo much pretend, I come now to</hi> prove this Charge against them, <hi>from two</hi> ſubſtantial Arguments.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1st. <hi>Their</hi> Diſobedience <hi>to their</hi> Lawful Superiours <hi>in Church and State:</hi> The Spirits of the Prophets, are Subject to the Prophets, <hi>1 Cor. 14.32.</hi> And the Spirit of God, perſwades and commands Men to Obey every Ordinance of Man, for the Lord's ſake, and to be ſubject to our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102911:51"/>Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Governours, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake, <hi>Rom. 13.5. 1 Pet. 2.13. But theſe Men by their</hi> cauſeleſs and ſinful Separation <hi>from our Church, make a Schiſme in it, as by their frequent</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of our rightful Kings, <hi>they have made</hi> Rebellions <hi>in the State,</hi> a thing which the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, were never guilty of, under the most bloody Perſecutions, but always abhor'd it as contrary to the good Spirit of God.</item>
                  <item>2dly. <hi>The</hi> baſe Railing, and filthy Language, <hi>which this</hi> Author and his Party <hi>do aften beſtow upon us; a brief account of which, I have before given, and ſhall now give an inſtance or two more of it,</hi> to fill up the Meaſure of his Iniquity, <hi>p. 44. ſpeaking of Men that uſe Forms of Prayers, (by which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt he marks out us) he ſays;</hi> They in Perſon appear as Hypocrites, and their Prayers are an abomination; when they ſay, they have been pouring out their Souls unto God, he ſaith they have been Howling like Dogs, and for this he quotes <hi>Hoſ. 7.14. tho 'tis plain, he here adds</hi>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:102911:52"/>to the Word of God, <hi>there being</hi> no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Dogs in that place, <hi>but only of</hi> the Children of <hi>Ephraims</hi> Howling upon their Beds; <hi>and this bold Man adds thereunto,</hi> like Dogs, <hi>to render us more odious in the application. But if we ſhould take the ſame liberty, and ſay, that theſe Men in their Conventicles,</hi> Groan and Grunt like Hogs, and Snarl and Bark like Dogs, <hi>tho' they</hi> cannot Bite and Devour us, <hi>I believe they would Proclaim us for the moſt Wicked and Uncharitable People in the World: For this very Man, on the Score of our ſlighting his Praying by the Spirit, (as I think I have ſufficiently prov'd we have Reaſon to do) breaks out into this ſtrange and horrid Exclamation:</hi> Is it not the Mark of implacable Reprobates? O fearful! Can you not be content to be Damn'd for your Sins against the Law; but you must Sin against the Holy Ghoſt? Good God! That we ſhould be accuſed of the Sin against the Holy Ghost, only for Vindicating his Honour, and expoſing ſuch Men as would father their Nonſenſe and Blaſphemies upon him! <hi>But in Truth,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102911:52"/>'tis</hi> theſe <hi>are the</hi> Blaſphemers of the Holy Spirit; <hi>'tis</hi> theſe <hi>are the</hi> Corahs <hi>and</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams of the Age, that Rebel against our <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and Curſe God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to their Face, even with bitter Words, and venemous Expreſſions, which ſhews them to be acted by the Inſtigation of another Spirit, even that of Satan and Antichriſt, who are all for Railing and Reviling, but the good Spirit of God, is all for mild, gentle and charitable Speeches, <hi>Jud. 9. Michael</hi> the Arch-angel, when contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Devil, he Diſputed about the Body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> durſt not bring againſt him a railing Accuſation, but ſaid, The Lord rebuke thee. <hi>The good Spirit of God, where'er he reſts, produces</hi> kind Thoughts, and charitable Expreſſions, <hi>both which,</hi> Jo. Bunyan <hi>is a Stranger to, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from p. 89.</hi> When Men Pray for a ſhew to be heard, and thought ſome body in Religion; there are two ſorts of Men, that Pray to this end, <hi>1ſt.</hi> Your Trencher-Chaplains, that thruſt themſelves into great Mens Families, pretending the Worſhip of God, when in truth, the great Buſineſs is their own Bellies, which were notably Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102911:53"/>out by <hi>Ahab</hi>'s Prophets, <hi>1 K. 18.</hi> and alſo <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Wiſe-men, <hi>Dan. 2.</hi> who, tho' they pretended great Devotion, yet their Luſts and their Bellies, were the great things aimed at by them in all their peices of Devotion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now can there be a</hi> greater <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſs <hi>ſhewn, than is couch'd in theſe few Words? Wherein all the</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains of great Men, without any exception, <hi>are repreſented as a Company of</hi> gorman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing Epicures, that make their Belly their God, and to be as bad as <hi>Ahab</hi>'s falſe Prophets, which fed at <hi>Jezabel</hi>'s Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and as bad as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Magicians, who were initiated into the Black-Art, and in a ſolemn League and Covenant with the Devil: <hi>Good God! That a Man ſhould publiſh to the World, ſuch</hi> Baſe and Scandalous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, on ſome Divines, <hi>who, for ought he knows to the contrary, may be as</hi> good Chriſtians <hi>and</hi> pious Perſons <hi>as any in the Nation;</hi> But if they call the Maſter of the Houſe <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> how much more ſhall they call them of his Houſhold? <hi>Mat. 10.25.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:102911:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>May we not with more Truth, call this Author a</hi> Corner-Chaplain? That follows his poor Creatures, that are delud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, into every Corner of the Houſe, and there makes them Groan most bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or elſe he could not ſay as he does <hi>p. 73.</hi> I know 'tis thus with them; their Groans go up to Heaven, from every Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Houſe; I know they do Groan, and that most bitterly: Of this ſort are they, that creep into Houſes, and lead Captive ſilly Women, laden with Sins; and that is enough to make them Groan indeed, <hi>2 Tim. 3.6.</hi> But if this does not pleaſe him, he muſt be contented to enjoy the Title of Tinker Chaplain, as most agreeable to his old Trade, tho' af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, for want of Charity, he proves to be but as ſounding Braſs, or a tinkling Cymbal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:102911:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR a farther Proof that</hi> Jo. Buny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's Pretences to the Spirit are vain, <hi>I ſhall produce</hi> his own Words <hi>in Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt him, where he adviſes Parents not to teach their Children to Pray by any Form, no not ſo much as the Lord's Prayer; and then being not of themſelves able to Pray extempore, they muſt not Pray at all</hi> Evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil indeed, and which never came from the good Spirit of God; <hi>it is p. 77.78.</hi> My Judgment is, (ſays he) that Men go the wrong Way, to learn their Children to Pray, in going about ſo ſoon to teach them a ſet company of Words, as is the common uſe of poor Creatures to do: For to me it ſeems to be a better way, for People betimes, to tell their Children what curſed Creatures they are, and how they are under the Wrath of God, by reaſon of original and actual Sin, as alſo to tell them the nature of Gods Wrath, and the duration of the Miſery; which if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:102911:54"/>do, they would ſooner learn their Children to Pray than they do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But tho' this Author gives his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the Style of St.</hi> Paul, <hi>yet does he ſhew by it, that he has not the Spirit of God, as St.</hi> Paul <hi>had; for that Apoſtle adviſes Parents thus,</hi> Epheſ. <hi>6.4.</hi> Ye Fathers provoke not your Children to Wrath; <hi>and to tell them,</hi> they are all curſed Creatures, <hi>in a</hi> damnable Condition, and obnoxious to Hell torments, which ſhall last for ever; <hi>one would think, were the ready way to</hi> provoke them to wrath indeed, <hi>but St.</hi> Paul <hi>ſays, provoke them not by any</hi> harſh Speeches <hi>at all, as theſe certainly are, which may ſooner drive them to</hi> Deſpair, <hi>than</hi> perſwade <hi>them to</hi> Pray; <hi>but (as he immediately ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns)</hi> bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord; <hi>and what can that import, but to teach them to ſay the</hi> Creed, Lord's Prayer, and Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, <hi>which contain the</hi> Sum and Subſtance of the Chriſtian Religion, <hi>even what we ought to</hi> believe and do, and how to Pray, <hi>in order to Salvation? But eſpecially to teach our Children to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102911:55"/>Pray according to that</hi> perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Form, <hi>which our Lord Jeſus has taught us, and left upon Record in the Goſpel, this is to Breed them up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord;</hi> and not the next way to make them curſed Hypocrites, and puff them up with Pride, as our uncharitable Author <hi>ſays it will, p. 78.</hi> I am confident, to tell little Children of Hell-fire and Damnation, and their own Wretched and Miſerable eſtate, (if they underſtand what we ſay) is the next way to cast them down into the Gulph of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair; <hi>and therefore our bleſſed Saviour took a quite contrary Courſe with them,</hi> Mark <hi>10.14.</hi> Suffer little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven; <hi>and v. 15.</hi> Whoſoever ſhall not receive the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God as a little Child, he ſhall not enter therein, <hi>and ver. 16.</hi> He took them up in his Arms, puts his Hands upon them, and Bleſſed them, <hi>which without doubt he did by ſome ſhort</hi> Form of Prayer, <hi>and ſo by</hi> that <hi>taught little</hi> Children to Pray alſo: <hi>Our Lord Jeſus to</hi> encourage <hi>little Children to be</hi> good betimes, <hi>ſays,</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:102911:55"/>of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>but</hi> J. Bunyan <hi>to</hi> diſcourage them, <hi>ſays,</hi> of ſuch is the Kingdom of Hell. <hi>Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes them</hi> as a Pattern of Meekneſs, Innocence, and Humility, <hi>Mat. 18.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. But</hi> John Bunyan ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes them as the Objects of Gods Wrath and Vengeance, and ſo many Brands of Hell-fire; <hi>and this he ſays,</hi> will make Tears run down your ſweet Babes Eyes, and hearty Groans to flow from your Hearts, <hi>tho' any one elſe would imagine this would ſwallow them up with overmuch Grief, and ſink their tender Spirits in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to downright Deſpair; and here I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but take notice how much this Man is for</hi> Groaning, <hi>ſince he would have</hi> Children to learn it, <hi>inſtead of</hi> their Prayers; <hi>Why? according to his way of Expounding Scripture,</hi> Rom. <hi>8.26. the</hi> Childrens Groanings <hi>may be as accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God, as the beſt of</hi> our Prayers, <hi>for, (as I obſerv'd before, Chap. 7.) he ſays,</hi> The Apoſtles could not ſo well come off, in the manner of performing this Duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When the Holy Ghost aſſiſted them, yet even then, they were
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:102911:56"/>fain to come off with Sighs and Groans, falling ſhort of expreſſing their Minds, but with Sighs and Groans which cannot be utter'd. (<hi>But how then could they</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>their Minds by them, if they were</hi> unutterable?) <hi>and cannot Children as well expreſs their Minds</hi> this way <hi>as the very</hi> Apoſtles themſelves, <hi>if they can but</hi> Groan luſtily, <hi>as he ſuppoſes the other to have done? So that our Author has found out a</hi> new Way, <hi>to teach Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to</hi> Pray, <hi>as well as their</hi> ungifted Brethren, <hi>'tis but for them to</hi> Groan well, <hi>and</hi> often, <hi>and</hi> loud, and the Work is done, and they may be ſaid to Pray as well as the Apoſtles ever did; <hi>and this</hi> Groaning will ſave them the labour of Reading the Bible, or Learning any Catechiſm that has the Lord's Prayer in it: O poor ſweet Babes! The Lord open your Eyes, and make you ſee, and ſhun the wicked and pernicious Counſel, of ſuch groaning Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I muſt farther obſerve, that</hi> J. Bunyan, <hi>does not in all his Advice here, put Parents upon Teaching their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to</hi> Read the Holy Scriptures, <hi>tho'</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:102911:56"/>Timothy <hi>had done it from a</hi> Child, <hi>and St.</hi> Paul <hi>commends him for it, 2</hi> Tim. <hi>3.15. And I doubt, the true Reaſon why he does not mention the Reading their Bibles, is for fear they ſhould meet with the</hi> Lord's Prayer <hi>in it, and ſo have a mind to learn by Heart, that</hi> excellent Form, <hi>which Chriſt himſelf has made, and enjoyned all his Diſciples to uſe; yet p. 79. he Quotes a Paſſage out of</hi> Pſalm. <hi>34.11. which is this,</hi> Come ye Children, hearken unto me, and I will Teach you the fear of the Lord: <hi>Which after his ſilly way, he Paraphraſes thus,</hi> David does not ſay, I will Nuzzle you up in a Form, but I will Teach you the fear of the Lord. <hi>Where, if the words refer to</hi> Children, <hi>and not</hi> Men, <hi>as they ſeem to do from the next Verſe,</hi> ver. <hi>12.</hi> What Man is he that deſireth Life? <hi>Yet,</hi> 1ſt. Jo. Bunyan <hi>uſes a</hi> Beaſtly Compariſon, <hi>in calling our Teaching Children, a</hi> Form of Prayer, a Nuzzling them up in it; <hi>which is an</hi> Expreſſion <hi>belonging to</hi> Hogs, <hi>whoſe young ones are ſaid to be</hi> Nuzzled up <hi>by them;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:102911:57"/>and 'tis a piece of</hi> Profane Wit, <hi>to compare the Teaching our Children</hi> God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Forms of Prayer, to the rearing up young Pigs; <hi>this is to</hi> offend and deſpiſe not only one, but all theſe little ones, <hi>tho' we are cautioned againſt it, at the</hi> Peril of our Souls; and least their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels Revenge the Contempt we throw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: <hi>Mat. 18.6.10.</hi> Whoſo ſhall offend one of theſe little ones which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in me, it were better that a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were hanged about his Neck, and that he were Drowned in the depth of the Sea: Take heed that ye deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones; for I ſay unto you, that in Heaven, their Angels do always behold the Face of my Father which is in heaven.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly. 'Tis plain, that</hi> David <hi>was for</hi> Educating Children in a Form, <hi>or elſe he had not kept the Commandment of the Lord, who required him to do it, as is evident from</hi> Deut. <hi>6.6, 7.</hi> And theſe Words which I command thee this Day ſhall be in thine Heart, <hi>(which relates chiefly to the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102911:57"/>mentioned in the 5th. Chapter)</hi> And thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy Children; and ſhalt talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thy Houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the Way; and when thou lyest down, and when thou riſeſt up: <hi>And Deut. 31.12.13.</hi> Gather the People to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Men, Women, and Children, and the Stranger that is within thy Gates, that they may hear, and that they may learn, and fear the Lord your God, and obſerve to do all the Words of this Law: <hi>And,</hi> What was all this, but the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Children Forms? <hi>So that</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>himſelf,</hi> (<hi>according to this Fellows</hi> unſeemly Compariſon) <hi>did</hi> Nuzzle up Children in Forms, or elſe he had diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed God, which required it; <hi>and the Teaching them ſuch Forms, is here called,</hi> the Teaching them the fear of the Lord; ſo unhappy ſtill is this Man, in urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Texts of Scripture, that they all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude against him, and for that very thing against which he produceth them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:102911:58"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOW after all, leaſt any ſhould cenſure me for ſpeaking</hi> too light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>of theſe Mens</hi> Groanings, <hi>and</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to Pray by the Spirit, <hi>I have this (which I preſume will be thought ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient by all Honeſt and Impartial Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) to offer in my Defence and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1st, That when I reflect on</hi> Jo. Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyan's Groanings, <hi>I do it only to ſhew his falſe and abſurd Interpretation of</hi> Rom. <hi>8.26. where he miſapplies the Groanings the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of, to himſelf and other Men, which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> belong to the Spirit of God, being ſuch as cannot be heard or uttered; <hi>as the Groanings of Men are, and I do not hereby condemn the</hi> Sighs and Graans <hi>which</hi> good People out of a deep Senſe of their Sins, and Sorrow for them, may,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:102911:58"/>and often do utter in their Cloſet, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, and private Ejaculations, which tho' none but God ſees and hears, yet he approves and accepts them the better, and meerly for their being Sincere and Secret, <hi>he will one</hi> Day, Reward them openly, <hi>Mat. 6.4.6.18. but as for ſuch</hi> Sighs and Groans, <hi>which are</hi> vented <hi>in the</hi> Congregation, (<hi>a thing conſtantly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed among the</hi> Quakers, <hi>as well as</hi> J. Bunyan and his Party, and other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters) <hi>we have no</hi> Precept <hi>or</hi> Example <hi>for them, either in the Old or New Teſtament. We read or hear of no ſuch thing in all their</hi> Religious Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; <hi>and particularly thoſe</hi> three great ones, <hi>wherein the Spirit of God aſſiſted in a more extraordinary manner, than he has ever done ſince that time; I mean when the Apoſtles and Diſciples, to the number of an Hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty met together, and Prayed to God to direct them in the choice of a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor to</hi> Judas; <hi>Acts 1.15.24. and when they were aſſembled on the Day of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt,</hi> Acts 2.1. when Three thouſand
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:102911:59"/>were Converted by St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>ver.</hi> 14.41. when the firſt great Council was aſſembled at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Act. 15.7.12. and when St. <hi>Paul</hi> Preached his farewel Sermon at <hi>Troas,</hi> continuing his Speech till Midnight, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. in all which places we read, that the People either <hi>kept Silence,</hi> or were <hi>ſorrowful and pricked to the Heart,</hi> or elſe <hi>ſpake in diverſe Tongues, the wonderful Works of God;</hi> but we do not find there <hi>was one Soul that Groan'd among them;</hi> which I the rather mention, becauſe all theſe were <hi>wonderful Converſions, and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Effuſions of the Holy Ghost;</hi> ſo little <hi>Authority from the Scripture, have any Diſſenters for the frequent Groanings which are heard among them, in their reſpective Meetings; or for their making theſe Groanings, an infallible Mark of their having the Spirit of God; they are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſometimes a Mark of Hypocriſie; and that thoſe that Delight and Pride themſelves in them, do this (as the Scribes and Phariſees did of old) only to be heard and ſeen of Men;</hi> Mat. 23.2.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102911:59"/>And therefore whatſoever good Men may do <hi>in private</hi> between God and their own Souls, when none ſees or hears but God alone; yet in <hi>publick,</hi> they are careful to avoid ſuch loud and frequent Groans, at leaſt to be very ſparing in them, leaſt inſtead of paſſing for <hi>Saints,</hi> they ſhould be taken for <hi>vain-glorious Hypocrites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> As for my ſlighting <hi>J. Bunyans</hi> and the Diſſenters Pretences to Pray by the Spirit, I muſt confeſs I do ſo in that Senſe they intend it, who imagine and ſay, That the Holy Spirit Invents and Dictates all the Words of their Prayer unto them; which is to make Almighty God, to multiply Miracles without neceſſity, and to make alſo, the <hi>Words of their Prayer as True, Infallible, and Divine, as the very Words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, being both equally Inſpired by the Holy Ghost;</hi> a thing that has not been known ſince the Apoſtolick Age, and <hi>then,</hi> it was always accompanyed <hi>with the Gift of Tongues;</hi> and the <hi>different
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:102911:60"/>and contradictory Prayers of the Quakers Anabaptiſts, Independents, and Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, (who all confidently pretend to Pray thus by the Spirit, and yet Pray one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another) is a ſufficient Confutation of it;</hi> for the <hi>Holy Spirit is one,</hi> and not <hi>contrary to himſelf;</hi> and all his Interceſſions for the Saints, are to the ſame end, in the ſame manner, and according to the ſame good Will and Pleaſure of Almighty God; <hi>but all this is Perform'd in a Secret, Inviſible, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nutterable way;</hi> and ſo is <hi>the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which he affords to good Men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by godly Motions, and holy Deſires, which are kindled within them, and which they can only feel in their Hearts, but not hear with their Ears, or expreſs with their Tongues;</hi> and ſuch an Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit, our <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> allows of, and teaches us to Pray for it; in the beginning of <hi>Morning and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Service,</hi> after Confeſſion of our Sins, the next Prayer (which is in Form of an <hi>Abſolution</hi>) runs thus; <hi>Wherefore let us beſeech him, to grant us true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102911:60"/>and his Holy Spirit, that thoſe things may pleaſe him, which we do at this preſent, and that the reſt of our Life hereafter may be Pure and Holy,</hi> &amp;c. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the repetition of the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, the <hi>Collect</hi> has theſe words in it, <hi>Cleanſe the Thoughts of our Hearts by the Inſpiration of thy Holy Spirit, that we may perfectly love thee, and worthily magnify thy Holy Name,</hi> &amp;c. In the <hi>Litany,</hi> one of the Petitions is; <hi>That it may pleaſe thee to give to all thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, increaſe of Grace, to hear meekly thy Word, and to receive it with pure Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to bring forth the Fruits of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And 'tis worth our Obſervation, that what ſome are pleas'd to call the <hi>Gift of Prayer,</hi> is not mentioned among the <hi>Fruits of the Spirit,</hi> which are all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſet down, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.23. as, <hi>Love, Joy, Peace, long Suffering, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance;</hi> neither is it reckoned among the <hi>Gifts of the Spirit,</hi> which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:102911:61"/>
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2. as, <hi>Wiſdom, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Counſel, Might, Knowledge, [Godlineſs] and the Fear of the Lord,;</hi> nor yet in, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8, 9, 10. where they are plac'd in this Order; <hi>The Word of Wiſdom, the Word of Knowledge, Faith, the Gifts of Healing, the working of Miracles, Prophecy, diſcerning of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, divers kinds and Interpretation of Tongues;</hi> in both which places, there is no mention of the <hi>Gift of Prayer,</hi> tho' in one of them, there is of the <hi>Gift of Prophecy;</hi> and therefore theſe Mens <hi>Pretences to Pray by the Spirit,</hi> as a <hi>peculiar Gift of his, has no Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in Holy Scripture; indeed, for any to expreſs themſelves well on a ſudden, and to Pray with variety and fluency of Words, is, and may be called a Gift of God; and ſo is Speech, Memory, and Invention, which nevertheleſs, are all common to good and bad Men, and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of being improved by induſtry and uſe, and more apt to Puff up than Edify, and to make ſuch as have them, deſpiſe and decry all that uſe Forms, as Formal
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:102911:61"/>Superſtitious and Graceleſs Men, that want the Life, Spirit, and Power of Prayer, and yet I doubt not, but many good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can teſtify this by their own Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that ſome notorious Hypocrites have this Gift of Prayer, and ſome devout and ſincere Chriſtians continue in the uſe of Forms, and reap the Comfort and Benefit of it:</hi> And 'tis farther obſervable, <hi>that all the Gifts of the Spirit</hi> enumerated by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> were of an <hi>extraordinary and miraculous Nature,</hi> as the <hi>Gift of Healing, diverſe kinds of Tongues, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miracles; and the Faith</hi> there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned among them, was not ſuch as is <hi>ordinary and ſaving,</hi> even to <hi>believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the true Meſſias and Saviour of the World;</hi> but it was a <hi>Faith of an extraordinary and miraculous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, even to believe that God would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to Work the Miracle they were about to perform before the People;</hi> for the Apoſtles never attempted to work a Miracle, till they had this <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Faith</hi> wrought in them firſt, by ſome <hi>Divine impulſe</hi> from the Spirit,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:102911:62"/>which aſſured them, that they ſhould certainly perform the Miracle they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook; for had the Apoſtles at any time failed in ſuch attempts, and ſet about a Miracle, which they were not able to work, it would have expoſed them mightily to the World, and giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en a great Blow to the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and made them and it, to be looked on as an Impoſture; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had always firſt a <hi>ſtrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Impulſe</hi> upon their Minds, (which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls alſo <hi>Faith</hi>) to aſſure them they could and ſhould be able to work the Miracle before ever they attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do it; but <hi>this</hi> and the <hi>other Gifts</hi> he there reckons up, were not <hi>ordinary and ſaving,</hi> which every good Chriſtian may now hope for, but they were <hi>extraordinary and miraculous,</hi> as is farther evident from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. <hi>But all theſe worketh that one and the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Spirit, dividing to every Man ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally as he will;</hi> i. e. no one Perſon had all theſe miraculous Gifts before mentioned, but they were variouſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:102911:62"/>among them; <hi>one had this, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother had that, another a third, and ſo on, and they all ceaſed in that Age;</hi> which cannot be ſaid of the <hi>ſaving Gifts and Graces</hi> of the Spirit, where he that has <hi>one in truth,</hi> has certainly <hi>all of them;</hi> as he that truely has ſaving Faith, has alſo Hope and Charity, Patience and Meekneſs in ſome meaſure; <hi>they being all knit together, as ſo many Links in the ſame Chain, that there can be no Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration made between them, and theſe ſhall never ceaſe;</hi> and the not <hi>underſtanding and conſidering this, is the main Cauſe I doubt, that many in this Age, expect and pretend to thoſe extraordinary and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Gifts of the Spirit, which are long ſince ceaſed, as St.</hi> Paul <hi>declares they ſhould,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.8.13. <hi>Charity ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faileth; but whether there be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies they ſhall fail, whether there be Tongues they ſhall ceaſe; whether there be Knowledge it ſhall vaniſh away; and now abideth Faith, Hope, Charity, theſe three, but the greateſt of theſe is Charity: But little or nothing of this,</hi> is to be <hi>found
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:102911:63"/>in all</hi> Jo. Bunyan's <hi>Book,</hi> which I have here Anſwered, as I believe any one will find, that does not think his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour loſt to read it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND thus having with his own Weapons, Vanquiſh'd this</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtical Goliah, <hi>that is</hi> Armed Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a-pee with Braſs, <hi>I ſhall cloſe all with this ſhort Addreſs to the</hi> Armies of our Iſrael; <hi>That they would</hi> every one of them get a Common Prayer Book, <hi>that is able to uſe it; and think himſelf</hi> Naked and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>narmed without it, as a Soldier does that is without his Sword; <hi>and that they would not only have their Common Prayer Books about them, but alſo make uſe of them in their dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Devotions; and not only uſe them, but</hi> put them alſo in Practiſe by their
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:102911:63"/>daily Converſation, in living a Godly, Righteous, and Sober Life, as they are therein taught to do; <hi>without this, tho' our Prayers are never ſo good, and we make never ſo many of them, they will ſignifie nothing, they will do us no more Service, than the</hi> Ark of God did the Iſraelites, when they relyed on it only for their Deliverance and Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and did not take care to walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Divine Preſence which reſided therein, and dwelt among them; <hi>1 Sam. 4.3.</hi> Let us fetch the Ark of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the Lord out of Shiloh unto us, that when he cometh among us, it may ſave us out of the Hand of our Enemies. <hi>Thus they thought, and earneſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but were ſoon convinced of the contrary, by the overthrow of their Army, and the taking of the Ark it ſelf, and carrying it in Triumph, into the Philiſtines Camp,</hi> ver. <hi>10, 11.</hi> And thus has it fared with our Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Book, when we too much reſted in it, and made uſe of it with Formality, Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs and Indifferency, and not with a
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:102911:64"/>ſuitable Zealand Devotion; it was twice thrown out of the Church, and taken from us, and carried Captive by our Adverſaries of <hi>Geneva</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> who, tho' they ſeem to ſtand at a diſtance, and defie one another, yet they both agree in this, to Hate our Common Prayer Book, and to do what they can to deſtroy it; and nothing but our walking unworthy of it, nothing but the Sins of our Prieſts, and the Iniquity of our People, can give them once more, their deſired Succeſs againſt it; <hi>wherefore, let all the Members of our Orthodox Church, ſhew their</hi> Soundneſs and Sincerity, <hi>by</hi> ſomething elſe, <hi>than the</hi> bare uſe of the Common Prayer <hi>in their reſpective Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; by</hi> ſomething elſe, <hi>than</hi> Drinking numerous Healths to the Proſperity of both; <hi>for I muſt needs ſay, ſuch</hi> numerous Healths <hi>as theſe, are one of the Diſeaſes ſhe at preſent labours under, and there is</hi> no hopes of a Cure, <hi>till all her</hi> Sons grow wiſe unto Sobriety; <hi>till they all ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> ſincere Chriſtians, and ſound Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, <hi>by</hi> ſomething elſe <hi>than</hi> bare Names, and meer outward Profeſſions; <hi>even by</hi> liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102911:64"/>Godly, Righteous, and Sober Lives, as our Common Prayer Book teaches us, to Pray every Day, in its general Confeſſion, and we are bound to Practice in our daily Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; in ſhort, our leading reformed Lives, and our Walking, as well as Praying according to the Common Prayer Book, <hi>is the beſt, the only</hi> way to Preſerve it, and the Reformed Religion among us.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
